<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980309.1618 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/09/1998 22:45:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2844 &Cx1f; wstm-
r s &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Sports-DogSledRacing-     03-09 0318
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Sports-Dog Sled Racing-Iditarod,0322 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Swenson leads Iditarod mushers into Rainy Pass
</HEADLINE>
&UR; Eds: RECAPS previous to update with Swenson leading &QL;
&UR; AP Photos &QL;
&UR; By ROSANNE PAGANO &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">RAINY PASS</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Alaska</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Five-time champion <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rick Swenson</ENAMEX> wasted
no time moving to the front of the pack in the Iditarod Trail Sled
Dog Race.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Swenson</ENAMEX> on Monday was the first musher to reach the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Rainy Pass</ENAMEX>
checkpoint, which is tucked deep in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Alaska Range</ENAMEX>. He arrived 90
minutes ahead of his nearest competitor, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Charlie Boulding</ENAMEX> of
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Manley</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Alaska</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vern Halter</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Willow</ENAMEX> arrived just four minutes
after <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Boulding</ENAMEX>.
With clear skies, the dog teams rested on beds of straw on
frozen <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puntilla Lake</ENAMEX>, surrounded by spectacular views of craggy,
snow-covered peaks.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mitch Seavey</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Sterling</ENAMEX> arrived in fourth place, two-time
champion <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeff King</ENAMEX> reached the checkpoint in fifth place. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mike
Nosko</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Wasilla</ENAMEX> arrived at in sixth place and rookie <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shawn
Sidelinger</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Wasilla</ENAMEX> was in seventh.
Mushers were pleased with snow conditions on the trail.
``I can't imagine anyone complaining about the trail,'' said
musher <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Linwood Fiedler</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Willow</ENAMEX>, who was first to leave the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Finger
Lake</ENAMEX> checkpoint for the to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Rainy Pass</ENAMEX>. ``It was a sprint trail as
far as I was concerned.''
Sixty-three teams _ including four past champions _ are entered
in this year's race, as well as 19 rookies and mushers from five
foreign countries.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Swenson</ENAMEX> added interest to the 26th Iditarod by reentering after
being withdrawn in 1996 when a dog in his team died along the
trail.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Swenson</ENAMEX>, who has never finished lower than 10th in 20 Iditarods,
bitterly protested, and the decision was overturned last year. But
he sat out 1997 anyway.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Swenson</ENAMEX> has said he's running in part to honor his dog Ariel,
who died of apparent strangulation in 1996.
``I'm as confident as anyone,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Swenson</ENAMEX> said.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Sports-Dog Sled Racing-Iditarod; CT:s;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-09-98 2245EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

