<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980227.0491 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 08:14:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2396 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Norway-Israel     02-27 0321
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Norway-Israel,0320 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Israeli prime minister to visit Norway, discuss peace process
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">OSLO</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Norway</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israeli</ENAMEX> Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Benjamin Netanyahu</ENAMEX> is
to discuss the deadlocked <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Middle East</ENAMEX> peace process in a three-day
visit to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Norway</ENAMEX> next week, officials said Friday.
The prospects for resuscitating the peace process have appeared
grim lately, but any visits by <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Middle East</ENAMEX> officials to the country
that guided the 1993 peace agreement raise speculation that a
breakthrough may be in the works.
``<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Norway</ENAMEX> has a central role in the peace process, and we
obviously will do what we can to contribute to the process going
further,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Norwegian</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Foreign Ministry</ENAMEX> spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ingvard Havnen</ENAMEX> told
the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Norwegian</ENAMEX> news agency <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTB</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Netanyahu</ENAMEX>'s visit is to run March 6-8, when he will meet both
with Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kjell Magne Bondevik</ENAMEX> and with Foreign Minister
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Knut Vollebaek</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israeli</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Embassy</ENAMEX> second secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnathan Meidan</ENAMEX>
told The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Associated Press</ENAMEX>.
Although the secret ``<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Oslo</ENAMEX> Channel'' talks that brought about
the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israel</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">PLO</ENAMEX> peace agreement were conducted under the former
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Social Democrat</ENAMEX>-led government, the new government that took power
in October is deeply interested in continuing its <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Middle East</ENAMEX>
influence.
Both <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vollebaek</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bondevik</ENAMEX> have visited <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israel</ENAMEX> since the
government took power, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Terje Roed-Larsen</ENAMEX>, a key figure in the
1993 process, was appointed last month as the new government's
special envoy for the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Middle East</ENAMEX>.
A senior <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> diplomat assured <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Palestinian</ENAMEX> leader <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yasser Arafat</ENAMEX>
on Thursday that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Washington</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> was resuming efforts to break the
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Mideast</ENAMEX> deadlock, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Palestinian</ENAMEX> officials said.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX> has asked <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israel</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Palestinians</ENAMEX> to
respond to a proposal that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israel</ENAMEX> withdraw from 13.1 percent of the
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Bank</ENAMEX> over 12 weeks. The withdrawal would take place in three
small stages, and each stage would be accompanied by <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Palestinian</ENAMEX>
security gestures.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Norway-Israel; CT:i;
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0814EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

