<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980213.1337 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/13/1998 14:43:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2139 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-ANALYSIS-Russia-US     02-13 0618
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-ANALYSIS-Russia-US,0617 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Iraq dispute underlines strain in U.S.-Russia ties
</HEADLINE>
&UR; With US-Iraq &QL;
&UR; An AP News Analysis &QL;
&UR; By BARRY RENFREW &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">MOSCOW</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> split over <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> underlines how
ties between <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Moscow</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Washington</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> have cooled as the Russians try
to reassert themselves as a world power.
While there is no danger of reviving the Cold War rivalry that
dominated the world for more than 45 years, the diplomatic
honeymoon that followed the collapse of the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Soviet Union</ENAMEX> in 1991 is
coming to an end.
Both <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Moscow</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Washington</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> value good relations, but there are
likely to be more and more disagreements as <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russia</ENAMEX> goes its own
way.
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russia</ENAMEX>'s opposition to the use of force in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> is the latest in
a series of foreign policy disputes with the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Moscow</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>
bitterly opposes <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NATO</ENAMEX> expansion in east <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Parliament</ENAMEX> has
blocked the START II missile-reduction treaty with <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Washington</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Moscow</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> also is building links with <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">China</ENAMEX>, saying the world must
not be dominated by the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX>.
President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Boris Yeltsin</ENAMEX> and other top <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> officials have
unleashed a barrage of warnings on <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> military strikes against
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yeltsin</ENAMEX> said last week a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> attack could lead to world war
and his defense minister, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Igor Sergeyev</ENAMEX>, publicly warned <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX>
Defense Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William Cohen</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Moscow</ENAMEX> against attacking <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>.
At the heart of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russia</ENAMEX>'s opposition are two issues.
On one level, the issue is mostly pragmatic. <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>, an old <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Soviet</ENAMEX>
client state, owes <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Moscow</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> billions of dollars for weapons that
can't be paid until <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> sanctions end. <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russia</ENAMEX>, its economy in
chaos, desperately needs the cash and also hopes for big new
contracts with <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> when sanctions end.
The second issue, emotive and unpredictable, is <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russia</ENAMEX>'s status
in the world. Many Russians yearn for the days when <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Moscow</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> was the
world's other superpower.
The fact that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russia</ENAMEX> has lost much of its power makes the need
to play a major global role all the more pressing for many <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX>
officials. And envy of its old rival, the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX>, is rising
as <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russia</ENAMEX>'s power continues to decline.
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> officials dismiss suggestions they would aid <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>
against the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Moscow</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> backs <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Nations</ENAMEX>' efforts to
strip <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> of weapons of mass production, but says only a
diplomatic solution can work.
Foreign Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yevgeny Primakov</ENAMEX>, who formed close ties in the
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Middle East</ENAMEX> as a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Soviet</ENAMEX> diplomat, has pushed for a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Moscow</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>-backed
solution on <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> to help restore <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> influence in the region.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> government has neither the desire or power to risk a
major confrontation with the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yeltsin</ENAMEX> considers good
relations with <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Washington</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> a foundation of his foreign policy.
But the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> government and many politicians will be
stridently critical of the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX> if they believe they are
being ignored. And <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> nationalists will use resentment of
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">American</ENAMEX> power to boost their calls to revive <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russia</ENAMEX> as a great
power.
Anti-<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">American</ENAMEX> resentment has increased as the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX> has
tried to influence <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> policy through economic leverage _
particularly in the hard-line parliament.
Some <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">American</ENAMEX> officials concede that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Washington</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> should be more
careful about <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> sensibilities. <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Moscow</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> should be courted as an
ally, they say, lending support to democratic government in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russia</ENAMEX>.
``I think it does reflect a sense here of resentment of being
ordered around, which in some cases I think our government has done
in a way that is not productive,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> Ambassador <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Collins</ENAMEX>
said recently.
----
EDITOR'S NOTE: <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barry Renfrew</ENAMEX> is The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Moscow</ENAMEX> bureau chief.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-ANALYSIS-Russia-US; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-13-98 1443EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

