<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980227.0485 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 08:06:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2390 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-EU-HumanitarianAid     02-27 0143
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-EU-Humanitarian Aid </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
EU clears dlrs 4 million for 9 African nations
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">BRUSSELS</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Belgium</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) - The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">EU</ENAMEX> on Friday cleared a dlrs 4
million package for humanitarian projects in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Somalia</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Kenya</ENAMEX>,
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tanzania</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Mozambique</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Djibouti</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Zanzibar</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Uganda</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Malawi</ENAMEX> and
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Madagascar</ENAMEX>.
It said dlrs 2.2 million will go to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Somalia</ENAMEX> to provide urgently
needed medical and food aid, the European Commission said in a
statement.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Kenya</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tanzania</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Mozambique</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Djibouti</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Zanzibar</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Uganda</ENAMEX> and
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Malawi</ENAMEX>, dlrs 1.6 million will help fight a cholera epidemic and
fund preventive health care measures.
Another dlrs 110,000 will go to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Madagascar</ENAMEX> which suffers from
food shortages, cyclones and locust plagues.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">EU</ENAMEX> funds will be channeled through humanitarian
organizations, including <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Medecins Sans Frontieres</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Red Cross</ENAMEX>
and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Unicef</ENAMEX>.
</TEXT>
&UR; (as-rw)
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-EU-Humanitarian Aid; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:MEST;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0806EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

