<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980219.0476 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/19/1998 08:02:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1151 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Cambodia-Britain-Host     02-19 0690
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Cambodia-Britain-Hostage </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Cambodian resistance general looking for remains of missing Briton
</HEADLINE>
 &UR; By DON PATHAN &QC; 
 &UR; Associated Press Writer &QC; 

<TEXT>
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">O'SMACH</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Cambodia</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ The top commander of a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Cambodian</ENAMEX>
resistance force said Thursday he has sent a team to recover the
remains of a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">British</ENAMEX> mine removal expert kidnapped and presumed
killed by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Khmer Rouge</ENAMEX> guerrillas almost two years ago.
	   Gen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nhek Bunchhay</ENAMEX>, a loyalist of ousted <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Cambodian</ENAMEX> Prime
Minister Prince <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Norodom Ranariddh</ENAMEX>, said in an interview with The
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Associated Press</ENAMEX> at his hilltop headquarters that he hopes to
recover the remains of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Christopher Howes</ENAMEX> within the next two weeks.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howes</ENAMEX> had been working for the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Britain</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mines Advisory
Group</ENAMEX> when he was abducted with his <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Cambodian</ENAMEX> interpreter Houn
Hourth in March 1996. There were many conflicting accounts of his
fate.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howes</ENAMEX>' team was clearing mines 17 kilometers (10 miles) from
<ENAMEX TYPE="FACILITY">Angkor Wat</ENAMEX>, the fabled 11th century temple that is <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Cambodia</ENAMEX>'s main
tourist attraction, when it was attacked.
	   In January this year, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">British</ENAMEX> police officers who had been
searching for <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howes</ENAMEX> concluded he had probably been killed soon
after being captured.
	   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Foreign Office</ENAMEX> said it had informed the family of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howes</ENAMEX>, 37
years old when he was kidnapped, that he probably died within weeks
or months of his capture on March 26, 1996.
	   ``Obviously, it is deeply discouraging for the family after 22
months, but there is no proof of life. But there is no evidence in
either direction _ that there is proof of life or death,'' said a
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Foreign Office</ENAMEX> spokesman, speaking with customary anonymity. ``We
will continue to do everything we can to establish what has
happened.''
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thai</ENAMEX> military officials who monitor <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Cambodian</ENAMEX> affairs said
privately Thursday that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Britain</ENAMEX>, through its embassies in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX>
and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Cambodia</ENAMEX>, has been pushing hard to resolve the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howes</ENAMEX> case as
the second anniversary of his abduction nears.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nhek Bunchhay</ENAMEX>, who had been closely involved in the search for
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howes</ENAMEX> before having to flee the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Cambodian</ENAMEX> capital after a coup
d'etat last year, appeared confident he would find <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howes</ENAMEX>' remains.
	   He said he received information from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Khmer Rouge</ENAMEX> guerrillas on
where the body had been buried, and recently ordered 10 of his men
from a force of 500 near <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Khmer Rouge</ENAMEX> headquarters in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Anlong Veng</ENAMEX> to
conduct the search.
	   If and when the remains are found, he said, they would be turned
over to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Embassy</ENAMEX>, apparently meaning they would be sent
across the border into <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX> and onward to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bangkok</ENAMEX>.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nhek Bunchhay</ENAMEX> said he now believed <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howes</ENAMEX> had been killed within
a week of his capture by a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Khmer Rouge</ENAMEX> faction loyal to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pol Pot</ENAMEX>,
then the guerrilla group's leader. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pol Pot</ENAMEX> is considered
responsible for the radical policies that led to the deaths of as
many as 1.7 million Cambodians when the communist group held power
in the late 1970s.
	   At the time <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howes</ENAMEX> was captured, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Khmer Rouge</ENAMEX> were a more or
less united guerrilla force with more than 10,000 men under arms.
But the group began to fall apart in mid-1996 after the defection
of one of its top leaders, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ieng Sary</ENAMEX>. Other commanders, and
thousands of guerrillas, followed him.
	   A small hardcore group under <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pol Pot</ENAMEX> continued to hold out at
their headquarters at <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Anlong Veng</ENAMEX> in northern Cambodia near the
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thai</ENAMEX> border.
	   But in June last year, the remaining leadership had a falling
out, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pol Pot</ENAMEX> was arrested.
	   In July last year in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Phnom Penh</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Cambodia</ENAMEX>'s capital, Second
Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hun Sen</ENAMEX> staged a successful coup d'etat against
First Prime Minister Prince <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Norodom Ranariddh</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ranariddh</ENAMEX>'s
loyalists, including <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nhek Bunchhay</ENAMEX>, his top military commander,
went into hiding or fled the capital.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nhek Bunchhay</ENAMEX>, evading an intensive manhunt, made his way to
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">O'Smach</ENAMEX>, the last major outpost held by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ranariddh</ENAMEX>'s forces. His men
have held the stronghold _ which is on the border just opposite the
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thai</ENAMEX> province of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Surin</ENAMEX> _ against repeated intense attacks by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hun
Sen</ENAMEX>'s troops. They have been aided by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Khmer Rouge</ENAMEX> guerrillas from
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Anlong Veng</ENAMEX>, who have formed an alliance with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ranariddh</ENAMEX>'s
resistance forces to oppose <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hun Sen</ENAMEX>. 	   
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Cambodia-Britain-Hostage; CT:i; 
(REG:ASIA;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-19-98 0802EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
