<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980219.0483 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/19/1998 08:04:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1158 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-France-UN-Iraq     02-19 0266
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-France-UN-Iraq </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
France optimistic about Annan mission to Baghdad
</HEADLINE>
 &UR; AP Photos Planned &QL; 

<TEXT>
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">PARIS</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> expressed optimism Thursday about <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX>
Secretary General <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kofi Annan</ENAMEX>'s visit to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Baghdad</ENAMEX>, with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Foreign
Ministry</ENAMEX> saying a diplomatic solution was still possible.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Annan</ENAMEX> is expected to arrive in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Paris</ENAMEX> early Thursday evening for
meetings with <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">French</ENAMEX> President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jacques Chirac</ENAMEX> and Foreign Minister
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hubert Vedrine</ENAMEX> before leaving for <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> on Friday morning.
	   ``We will reiterate our support for the Secretary General's
mission, which should lead to a diplomatic solution of the
crisis,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">French</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Foreign Ministry</ENAMEX> spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yves Doutriaux</ENAMEX> told a
regular news briefing Thursday.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> has cautioned the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX> against leading a
military strike against <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Baghdad</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> in the belief that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam Hussein</ENAMEX>
may still back down and agree to unrestricted access for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX>
weapons inspectors to all sites.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Chirac</ENAMEX> was expected to stress to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Annan</ENAMEX> that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> wants a
peaceful solution to the crisis. Unlike <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Britain</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> has not
contributed to a buildup of Western forces in the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Persian Gulf</ENAMEX>.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX>'s interior minister, an outspoken critic of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> policy
in the Gulf, has criticized what he called ``<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">American</ENAMEX> diplomacy's
will for war'' and said the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX> should have shown such
resolve during World War II.
	   Under <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> resolutions following the 1991 Gulf War that followed
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>'s invasion of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Kuwait</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Baghdad</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> must destroy its biological,
chemical and nuclear weapons programs before a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> trade embargo
can be lifted.
	   (parf-dgs) 	   
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-France-UN-Iraq; CT:i; 
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-19-98 0804EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

