<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980227.0468 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 07:56:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2373 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Russia-Kalashnikov'sM 1stLd   02-27 0148
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Russia-Kalashnikov's Museum, 1st Ld </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Moscow mayor donates funds to build Kalashnikov museum
</HEADLINE>
&UR; Eds: SUBS 3rd graf to conform to AP style. &QL;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">MOSCOW</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ The mayor of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Moscow</ENAMEX> has allocated funds to help
build a museum in honor of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mikhail Kalashnikov</ENAMEX>, the Russian who
gave his name to the world's most widely wielded weapon, according
to a news agency report Friday.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kalashnikov</ENAMEX> designed the AK-47 automatic rifle, famed for its
reliability and effectiveness. Together with its derivatives, the
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kalashnikov</ENAMEX> rifle has been used by the police and armies of 55
countries and an assortment of guerrillas, terrorists and just
plain thugs around the globe.
Seventy-five million copies of the rifle have been built since
it entered production in February 1947, making it history's most
widely distributed weapon.
&UR; The ITAR-Tass, 4th graf pvs
(pvs/ji)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Russia-Kalashnikov's Museum, 1st Ld; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0756EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

