<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980301.0180 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/01/1998 06:18:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2674 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Israel-Hamas     03-01 0223
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Israel-Hamas </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Hamas militants go on trial in Israel
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">JERUSALEM</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Two <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Islamic</ENAMEX> militants suspected of killing an
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israeli</ENAMEX> soldier and plotting a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tel Aviv</ENAMEX> bombing went on trial
Sunday, and a Palestinian charged with helping finance <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hamas</ENAMEX>
activists was brought before judges.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jamal al-Hor</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Abdel Rahman Ghanimat</ENAMEX> are charged in an <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israeli</ENAMEX>
military court in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Lod</ENAMEX> of running a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hamas</ENAMEX> squad that is blamed for
the deaths of 11 Israelis over the past two years.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hor</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ghanimat</ENAMEX> allegedly ran the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Islamic</ENAMEX> militant <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hamas</ENAMEX>
group's cell in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Bank</ENAMEX> village of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tsurif</ENAMEX>, north of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Hebron</ENAMEX>.
The cell has been blamed for three drive-by shootings, the
abduction and slaying of an <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israeli</ENAMEX> soldier, and a March suicide
bombing in a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tel Aviv</ENAMEX> cafe that killed three women.
Also Sunday, the court was to extend the detention of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mohammed
Othman</ENAMEX>, a 25-year-old from the <ENAMEX TYPE="FACILITY">Shuafat refugee camp</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Jerusalem</ENAMEX>
accused of running the banned <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Holy Land Foundation</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israel</ENAMEX> outlawed the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Richardson</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Texas</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Holy Land Foundation</ENAMEX>
last year, saying it transfers funds to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hamas</ENAMEX> activists and gives
money to the families of suicide bombers.
According to the charge sheet against <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Othman</ENAMEX>, also known as
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rahman Anati</ENAMEX>, the group transferred funds through him to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hamas</ENAMEX>
activists in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israel</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Bank</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Gaza</ENAMEX>.
</TEXT>
&UR; ga-hla
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Israel-Hamas; CT:i;
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-01-98 0618EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

