<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980213.1325 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/13/1998 14:36:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2127 &Cx1f; wstm-
r s &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Sports-Tennis-St.Pete     02-13 0151
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Sports-Tennis-St. Petersburg Open,0153 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Krajicek a step closer to St. Petersburg Open win
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">ST. PETERSBURG</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russia</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Top seed <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard Krajicek</ENAMEX> of the
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Netherlands</ENAMEX> downed eighth-seeded <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Czech</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Daniel Vacek</ENAMEX> in straight
sets Friday to advance to the semifinals of the St. Petersburg
Open.
The 1996 Wimbledon champion beat <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vacek</ENAMEX> 7-6 (7-4), 6-1.
Fourth-seeded <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marc Rosset</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Switzerland</ENAMEX> breezed past <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Slovakia</ENAMEX>'s
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dominik Hrbaty</ENAMEX>, seeded sixth, 6-4, 6-3 and second seed <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cedric
Pioline</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> outlasted unseeded <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hendrik Dreekmann</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Germany</ENAMEX>
4-6, 6-3, 7-5.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thomas Johansson</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Sweden</ENAMEX>, who won the 1996 competition who is
seeded fifth, ousted third-seeded <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fabrice Santoro</ENAMEX> 6-3,
6-3. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johansson</ENAMEX> goes against <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Krajicek</ENAMEX> in the semifinals.
In doubles, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">South Africans</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marius Barnard</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brent Haygarth</ENAMEX>
beat fellow countrymen <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John-Laffnie Dejager</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robbie Koenig</ENAMEX> 6-3,
6-4.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Sports-Tennis-St. Petersburg Open; CT:s;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-13-98 1436EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

