<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980430.1644 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 04/30/1998 23:35:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2300 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Thailand-ExcrementHur     04-30 0142
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Thailand-Excrement Hurler </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Thai court fines man who threw excrement at commerce minister
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">BANGKOK</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Criminal Court</ENAMEX> has fined a
law tutor who threw a bag of human excrement at the minister of
commerce in 1994, The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bangkok Post</ENAMEX> reported Friday.
Judge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Somchai Panthmnopas</ENAMEX> imposed a 6,000-baht (dlrs 155) fine
and a suspended one-year jail term on <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thanit Suwanmena</ENAMEX> on Thursday,
the paper said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thanit</ENAMEX> hurled the bag of excrement at Commerce Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Uthai
Pimchaichon</ENAMEX> during a press conference in 1994. It exploded on
impact when it hit <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Uthai</ENAMEX>'s face.
The tutor said he was angry that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Uthai</ENAMEX> had reinstated a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Commerce
Ministry</ENAMEX> official accused of corruption.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Uthai</ENAMEX> was one of the chief drafters of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX>'s new
constitution, which is designed to reduce corruption and increase
civil rights.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Thailand-Excrement Hurler; CT:i;
(REG:ASIA;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-04-30-98 2335EDT
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

