<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980213.1313 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/13/1998 14:28:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2115 &Cx1f; wstm-
r s &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Sports-Tennis-Paris     02-13 0223
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Sports-Tennis-Paris </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Novotna advances to semi-finals at Paris Open
</HEADLINE>
&UR; Eds: will be UPDATED with friday's final quarter-final &QL;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">PARIS</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Top seed <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jana Novotna</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">the Czech Republic</ENAMEX>
recovered from a second set trouncing to advance to the semi-finals
of the Paris Open Friday, beating seventh-seed <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barbara Paulus</ENAMEX>, of
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Austria</ENAMEX>, 6-2, 1-6, 6-4.
``That was one tough match,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Novotna</ENAMEX>, 29, said. ``I'm just
happy I came out a winner.''
Winner of the season-ending Chase Championships and currently
ranked third in the world, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Novotna</ENAMEX> now meets <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Germany</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Anke Huber</ENAMEX>,
seeded fifth, in Saturday's semi-finals.
The dlrs 480,000 Paris Open is <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Novotna</ENAMEX>'s first tournament of the
year.
In other action, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Belgium</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dominique Van Roost</ENAMEX>, seeded sixth,
beat the 1997 French Open champion <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Iva Majoli</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Slovakia</ENAMEX>, 7-5
6-3.
Both players were treated for injuries during play, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Van Roost</ENAMEX>
suffering from stiffness in the forearm and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Majoli</ENAMEX> with a
right-ankle strain.
``I played really good tennis today except at the start. I have
a flat-hitting game and I can take the risks I want to take when I
play indoors, '' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Van Roost</ENAMEX> said.
The Belgian will now match up with the winner of the all-<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">French</ENAMEX>
duel later Friday between <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nathalie Tauziat</ENAMEX>, seeded fourth, and
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sarah Pitkowski</ENAMEX>.
(ap-ip)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Sports-Tennis-Paris; CT:s;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-13-98 1428EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

