<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980418.0210 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 04/18/1998 06:07:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1416 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Hungary-Astronaut     04-18 0248
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Hungary-Astronaut </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
First and only Hungarian astronaut moving to the United States
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">BUDAPEST</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Hungary</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Tired of being sidelined, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Hungarian</ENAMEX>
astronaut <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bertalan Farkas</ENAMEX> is leaving for the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX> to start
a new career, he said Saturday.
``Being 48 is too early to be retired,'' a fit-looking <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Farkas</ENAMEX>
said on state TV's morning talk show.
With <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">American</ENAMEX> astronaut <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jon McBride</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Farkas</ENAMEX> set up an
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">American</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Hungarian</ENAMEX> joint venture called <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Orion 1980</ENAMEX>, manufacturing
space-travel related technology.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Farkas</ENAMEX> will move to the company's <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> headquarters.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Farkas</ENAMEX>, an air force captain, was sent into space on board the
Soyuz 36 on May 26, 1980. He spent six days aboard the Salyut 6
spacecraft with three <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Soviet</ENAMEX> astronauts, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Valery Kubasov</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Leonid
Popov</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Valery Riumin</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">McBride</ENAMEX>, 54, of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Lewisburg</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">West Virginia</ENAMEX>, was part of a
seven-member crew aboard the Orbiter Challenger in October 1984 and
later served as assistant administrator for congressional relations
for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NASA</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Farkas</ENAMEX> expressed the hope he could one day follow in the
footsteps of fellow astronaut <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Glenn</ENAMEX>, who at 77 is about to go
into space again.
On May 22, 1995, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Farkas</ENAMEX> was made a brigadier general, and the
following year he was appointed military attache at the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Hungarian</ENAMEX>
embassy in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Washington</ENAMEX>.
However, cited by <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">District of Columbia</ENAMEX> traffic police in
ordered home and retired.
(ab/dc)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Hungary-Astronaut; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-04-18-98 0607EDT
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

