<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980306.1001 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/06/1998 13:19:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2188 &Cx1f; wstm-
u i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Iraq 3rdLd-Writethru   03-06 0642
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Iraq, 3rd Ld-Writethru </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
American Ritter resumes inspections in Iraq
</HEADLINE>
&UR; Eds: AMs; RECASTS throughout with Ritter inspecting three sensitive
sites; UN quotes &QL;
&UR; By LEON BARKHO &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">BAGHDAD</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ An <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">American</ENAMEX> leader of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> weapons
inspection team resumed work in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> Friday, nearly two months
after his team was effectively blocked.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Scott Ritter</ENAMEX> led his team on a 10-hour tour of three suspected
weapons sites classified as ``sensitive'' by the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraqi</ENAMEX> authorities,
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alan Dacey</ENAMEX> said.
``All sites were inspected to the satisfaction of the inspection
team and with full cooperation of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraqi</ENAMEX> authorities,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dacey</ENAMEX> said.
At least one of the sensitive sites was a barracks of the elite
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Republican Guard</ENAMEX>, a well-placed source told <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">The Associated Press</ENAMEX>.
Previously the Iraqis have resisted attempts to inspect such
quarters.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> Security Council</ENAMEX> has charged the inspectors with
verifying that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> has destroyed its long-range missiles and
weapons of mass destruction.
It was the first time that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ritter</ENAMEX>, who arrived Thursday with
some 50 inspectors for a tour likely to last over a week, had been
allowed to carry out an inspection since Jan. 13.
Then the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Baghdad</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> government stopped providing <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ritter</ENAMEX>'s team with
escorts, making it impossible for him to enter any site. <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>
alleged <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ritter</ENAMEX> was an <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">American</ENAMEX> spy whose team had a
disproportionately high number of Americans and Britons.
The official <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Iraqi News Agency</ENAMEX>, which gives the daily tally of
inspections, did not mention <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ritter</ENAMEX> by name, but said Friday that
team no. 225 _ which <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ritter</ENAMEX> heads _ made surprise visits to a
number of sites and was assisted by aerial surveillance.
Five other <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> inspection teams visited a total of nine other
sites, the agency reported.
An <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraqi</ENAMEX> official, speaking on customary condition of anonymity,
said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ritter</ENAMEX> would not try to visit any of the eight presidential
sites that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Baghdad</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> had placed off-limits to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> weapons
inspectors.
The official said these sites could only be visited by a special
team of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> monitors and diplomats as laid down by the Feb. 23
accord signed by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> Secretary-General <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kofi Annan</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraqi</ENAMEX> Deputy
Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tariq Aziz</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ritter</ENAMEX>'s return is seen as something of a test of that
agreement, under which <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> agreed to give inspectors full access
to eight of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam Hussein</ENAMEX>'s presidential palaces.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX> had moved additional troops and a naval armada
into the Gulf and said it would strike <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> unless it gave the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX>
arms inspectors unfettered access to all potential weapons sites,
including <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam</ENAMEX>'s palaces. <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> had argued the presidential sites
should be off limits as symbols of sovereignty.
A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="FACILITY">Pentagon</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> spokesman said Thursday that the 38,000 <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> troops
in the Gulf will remain until <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> complies with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N. Security
Council</ENAMEX> agreement over weapons inspections.
``We are going to maintain our forces in the region for the
foreseeable future,'' said spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kenneth Bacon</ENAMEX>.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> accord was worked out by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> Secretary-General
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kofi Annan</ENAMEX>, who appointed a retired <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Indian</ENAMEX> diplomat on Thursday as
his special representative to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Prakash Shah</ENAMEX>, 58, a former
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Indian</ENAMEX> ambassador to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Nations</ENAMEX>, is part of an effort by
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Annan</ENAMEX> to expand contacts with the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraqi</ENAMEX> leadership.
Palace inspections are not expected to start until the new
agreement's procedures are in place. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> officials in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">New York</ENAMEX> on
Friday finished drafting the rules, in consultation with <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraqi</ENAMEX>
diplomats. The procedures are due to go before the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Security Council</ENAMEX>
next week.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Security Council</ENAMEX> has said it will not lift the sweeping
the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> inspectors certify that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Baghdad</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> has eliminated its weapons
of mass destruction.
</TEXT>
&UR; lb-jbm
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Iraq, 3rd Ld-Writethru; CT:i;
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-06-98 1319EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>


