<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980227.0464 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 07:54:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2369 &Cx1f; wstm-
r s &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Sports-Boxing-Chatcha     02-27 0149
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Sports-Boxing-Chatchai-Kim </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Thailand's Chatchai retains WBC flyweight title
</HEADLINE>
&UR; Eds: Judges' names not available &QL;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">BANGKOK</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Chatchai Sasakul</ENAMEX> retained
his <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">World Boxing Council</ENAMEX> flyweight title Friday, winning by
unanimous decision of the judges over <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">South Korea</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kim Yong-jin</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Chatchai</ENAMEX>, 28, entered the bout held on the southern <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thai</ENAMEX> resort
island of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Koh Samui</ENAMEX> with a professional record of 31 wins,
including 23 knockouts, and one loss.
Ninth-ranked challenger <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kim</ENAMEX>, also 28, had a record of 20 wins,
with 13 knockouts, against two losses and one draw, before Friday's
fight.
Although <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Chatchai</ENAMEX> had been heavily favored, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kim</ENAMEX> put up a
credible fight, but did not connect with enough punches to
seriously threaten the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thai</ENAMEX> champion.
One judge scored the fight 117-111, while the other two both
scored it 119-111 in the Thai's favor.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Sports-Boxing-Chatchai-Kim; CT:s;
(REG:ASIA;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0754EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

