<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980227.0498 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 08:21:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2403 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Thailand-Burma-Milita     02-27 0459
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Thailand-Burma-Military </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Burmese troops chasing rebels reported on Thai soil
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">CHIANG MAI</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thai</ENAMEX> army is in a standoff
against more than 500 <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Burmese</ENAMEX> government troops who crossed into
northern <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Thailand</ENAMEX> in pursuit of ethnic insurgents and have refused
to retreat, a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thai</ENAMEX> border official said Friday.
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Burmese</ENAMEX> troops are holding their ground about five kilometers
(three miles) inside <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX> at the Tong Na <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">village</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Pang Ma Pa
district</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Mae Hong Son province</ENAMEX>.
The Burmese are claiming the right to be there on the basis that
the area has yet to be demarcated, he said. He said about 100 of
the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Burmese</ENAMEX> troops have been on <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thai</ENAMEX> soil since Tuesday and 400
more troops have crossed over to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX> since then.
A <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thai</ENAMEX> army official in the area, however, dismissed the
incident as ``minor,'' insisting that only several dozen <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Burmese</ENAMEX>
troops had ``accidentally'' crossed over on Wednesday but that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thai</ENAMEX>
soldiers had pushed them back.
He said he had sent more troops to monitor the situation, as
requested by provincial authorities, and insisted that everything
was under control.
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thai</ENAMEX> officials often downplay incidents of border tension to
avoid diplomatic wrangles with <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Burma</ENAMEX>.
Although <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thai</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Burmese</ENAMEX> relations are generally good, disputes
over the demarcation of the border, as well as the presence of
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Burmese</ENAMEX> ethnic minority guerrillas, has led to a number of
confrontations.
The border official said the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Burmese</ENAMEX> troops were planning to
attack guerrillas of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shan State Army</ENAMEX> troops from <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thai</ENAMEX> territory
and forced civilian refugees, who are about two kilometers (one
mile) from the border, to return to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Burma</ENAMEX>.
He said the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thai</ENAMEX> army had requested help from border patrol
police and some paramilitary <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ranger</ENAMEX> units, who arrived in the area
with mortars and machine guns. Several helicopters have been
requested as well, he said.
out about a week ago inside <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Burma</ENAMEX> near the city of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Homong</ENAMEX>, the
former headquarters of opium warlord <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Khun Sa</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Khun Sa</ENAMEX>, also known
as <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Chang Qifu</ENAMEX>, surrendered to the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Burmese</ENAMEX> government in 1996 and is
now thought to be living in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Rangoon</ENAMEX>.
When <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Khun Sa</ENAMEX> surrendered, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Burma</ENAMEX>'s military government said most
of his 10-15,000 ethnic Shan troops had laid down their arms and
the area was under government control.
But recently, three separate Shan rebel armies announced they
were joining forces to continue the war against the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Burmese</ENAMEX> regime.
The renewed guerrilla war has been a setback for the military
government in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Rangoon</ENAMEX>, which has touted ceasefires with many ethnic
insurgent groups as one of its accomplishments.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Thailand-Burma-Military; CT:i;
(REG:ASIA;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0821EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

