<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980227.0469 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 07:57:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2374 &Cx1f; wstm-
r s &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Sports-Soccer-NoTicke     02-27 0582
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Sports-Soccer-No Tickets </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
England presses for tickets; warns of hooligan problems
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">LONDON</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Government ministers, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">parliament</ENAMEX> members and
soccer officials pressed their demands Friday that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">England</ENAMEX> should
receive more tickets for this summer's World Cup in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> to avoid
giving hooligans an excuse to cause trouble.
Sports Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tony Banks</ENAMEX> termed ``miserly'' the allocation of
only 9,128 tickets for <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">England</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>'s first three games. Home Secretary
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jack Straw</ENAMEX> warned that demand would exceed supply even if the
allocation were doubled or tripled.
``The demand would still outstrip supply by a factor 100 or
1,000,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Straw</ENAMEX> said, warning of danger if fans without tickets
swarm into <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX>.
``What is absolutely critical is that we must not let this
controversy about the relatively low level of ticket allocation be
used as an excuse to justify... criminals and hooligans causing
trouble at the games,'' added <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Straw</ENAMEX>, the minister in charge of
policing.
Several other <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">European</ENAMEX> countries _ <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Germany</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Belgium</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">the
Netherlands</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Denmark</ENAMEX> among them _ have had similar complaints
about <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX>'s ticketing policy, brought about by relatively small
stadiums and an increase of World Cup finalists from 24 to 32.
``This is making something of a mockery of a great footballing
festival,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Banks</ENAMEX> said.
Twenty-two members of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">parliament</ENAMEX> also weighed in Friday with a
motion condemning ``the action of the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">French</ENAMEX> ticketing
authorities,'' terming it a breach of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">European Commission</ENAMEX>
regulations.
The motion calls on Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tony Blair</ENAMEX>, serving in the
swift punitive action and a proper allocation of tickets for
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">British</ENAMEX> fans hoping to attend this festival of football.''
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">English Football Association</ENAMEX> has also asked soccer's world
governing body <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FIFA</ENAMEX> to press the French for more tickets.
``We will take this as far as we possible can,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FA</ENAMEX>
spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Davies</ENAMEX>. ``At the moment our concern has gone to
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FIFA</ENAMEX> General Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sepp Blatter</ENAMEX>. We know there is deep concern
and that has been reflected in the telephone conversation we've had
right across <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Europe</ENAMEX>.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Straw</ENAMEX>, speaking Friday at a roundtable on hooliganism and
security in the northern city of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Blackburn</ENAMEX>, warned fans not to
travel to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> without tickets.
``Despite what anyone claims _ no one has tickets, as they have
yet to be printed,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Straw</ENAMEX> said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Straw</ENAMEX> also pointed out that under <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">French</ENAMEX> law, tickets are
invalid ``unless they are bought from an authorized agent.''
Under the current allocation, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">England</ENAMEX> will receive 3,790 tickets
for its opening match against <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tunisia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Marseille</ENAMEX> on June 15;
2,749 for the game against <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Romania</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Toulouse</ENAMEX> on June 22; and
2,589 for the match against <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Colombia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Lens</ENAMEX> on June 26.
The stadium capacity is 60,000 in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Marseille</ENAMEX>, 37,000 in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Toulouse</ENAMEX>
and 41,000 in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Lens</ENAMEX>.
There are a total of 2.5 million tickets on sale for the 64
matches during the tournament.
Under <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FIFA</ENAMEX>'s rules:
_ 65 percent of the tickets are sold in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX>, with priority to
the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">French</ENAMEX> soccer family.
_ 10 percent are sold to officially approved tour operators.
_ 5 percent are made available for purchase by official sponsors
and partners.
_ 20 percent are reserved for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FIFA</ENAMEX> and the national
associations, with 80 percent of those going to the two countries
playing a match, on the basis of each team getting half.
(scw/sw)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Sports-Soccer-No Tickets; CT:s;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0757EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
