<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980219.0507 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/19/1998 08:15:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1180 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-SwissBanks-Nazis     02-19 0425
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Swiss Banks-Nazis,0425 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Swiss government rejects Jewish refugee's compensation claim
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">BERN</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Switzerland</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Swiss</ENAMEX> government has rejected the
compensation claim of a World War II Jewish refugee who claimed the
country was responsible for his parents' deaths, it was announced
Thursday.
	   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Department of Finance</ENAMEX> said in a statement that the
claim filed last year by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Charles Sonabend</ENAMEX> had no legal ground. The
demand related to events too far in the past, it said.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sonabend</ENAMEX>, 66, who now lives in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">London</ENAMEX>, sought 100,000 <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Swiss</ENAMEX>
francs (dlrs 69,000), saying the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Swiss</ENAMEX> authorities' asylum policy
led to his parents' deaths.
	   In 1942, the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sonabend</ENAMEX> family fled to neutral <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Switzerland</ENAMEX> from
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nazi</ENAMEX>-occupied <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Belgium</ENAMEX>. According to a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Swiss</ENAMEX> television report in
October, the family was arrested and deported to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> two days
later. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sonabend</ENAMEX>'s parents later died at the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Auschwitz</ENAMEX> concentration
camp.
	   The department said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sonabend</ENAMEX> can appeal to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Switzerland</ENAMEX>'s supreme
court.
	   ``The federal authorities, unlike the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nazi</ENAMEX> regime, didn't commit
war crimes,'' the department said. ``The government expresses its
deeply felt sympathy and regret, independently of the judicial
assessment of the request and of the historical evaluation of the
circumstances.''
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sonabend</ENAMEX>'s attorney, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marc Richter</ENAMEX>, said in a statement that he
will appeal. He described as ``cheap'' the government's
justification for turning down the claim.
	   Surrounded by <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Germany</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nazi</ENAMEX>-occupied <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nazi</ENAMEX>-allied
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italy</ENAMEX>, wartime <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Switzerland</ENAMEX> took in nearly 30,000 Jews. But it
turned away an equal number, many of them to a certain death.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Switzerland</ENAMEX> has been accused of acting as <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX>'s banker, and
its banks has been criticized for dragging their feet over allowing
Holocaust victims' heirs access to dormant accounts. But it has
also been praised for its efforts to investigate fully what
happened and make amends for any wrongdoing.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">The committee of independent historians</ENAMEX> set up to investigate
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Switzerland</ENAMEX>'s wartime past said Thursday that its full report on
the country's gold transactions with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nazi</ENAMEX> regime will be
released April 7.
	   The panel's preliminary report in December said <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Switzerland</ENAMEX> was
involved in 76 percent of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nazi</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Germany</ENAMEX>'s gold transactions during
World War II. It added that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Swiss</ENAMEX> banks handled dlrs 450 million in
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nazi</ENAMEX> gold _ a portion of which had been looted.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Switzerland</ENAMEX>'s major banks have set up a fund to help needy
survivors of the Holocaust, especially those still living in
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Eastern Europe</ENAMEX>. 	   
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Swiss Banks-Nazis; CT:i; 
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-19-98 0815EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

