<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980213.1340 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/13/1998 14:44:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2143 &Cx1f; wstm-
u s &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Sports-Soccer-Panucci     02-13 0178
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Sports-Soccer-Panucci </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Italian defender Panucci says he won't go back to Milan
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">MADRID</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Spain</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italian</ENAMEX> defender <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Christian Panucci</ENAMEX> ruled
out reports Friday that he planned to leave <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Real Madrid</ENAMEX> and rejoin
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fabio Capello</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AC Milan</ENAMEX>, saying he intended to finish his
six-season contract with the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Spanish</ENAMEX> club.
``I wouldn't go to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Milan</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> for a billion,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Panucci</ENAMEX>, sitting
alongside <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Madrid</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lorenzo Sanz</ENAMEX>, told a press conference.
``I am very happy here.''
A former <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Milan</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> star, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Panucci</ENAMEX> signed for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Real Madrid</ENAMEX> half-way
through last season while <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Capello</ENAMEX> was coach of the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Spanish</ENAMEX> side and
led it to win the league championship. He is under contract until
2003.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sanz</ENAMEX> said that anyone who wanted to buy <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Panucci</ENAMEX> before that
would have to pay the 15 billion pesetas (dlrs 100 million)
stipulated.
Talk that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Panucci</ENAMEX> might follow <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Capello</ENAMEX> back home increased in
recent weeks with poor performances leading him to be frequently
placed on the substitutes' bench by current <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Madrid</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> coach <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Juup
Heynckes</ENAMEX>.
(cg)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Sports-Soccer-Panucci; CT:s;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-13-98 1444EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

