<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980227.0489 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 08:13:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2394 &Cx1f; wstm-
u i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-OAU-Rwanda     02-27 0216
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-OAU-Rwanda </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
OAU to investigate Rwandan genocide
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">ADDIS ABABA</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ethiopia</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Organization of African Unity</ENAMEX>
said Friday it would investigate the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hutu</ENAMEX>-organized genocide of
more than 500,000 minority Tutsis in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Rwanda</ENAMEX> nearly four years ago.
Foreign ministers of member-states meeting in the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ethiopian</ENAMEX>
capital agreed to set up a seven-member panel to investigate who
shot down <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Rwandan</ENAMEX> President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Juvenal Habyarimana</ENAMEX>'s plane on April 6,
1994.
The assassination touched off a murderous rampage by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hutu</ENAMEX>
security forces and civilians, who slaughtered mainly Tutsis but
also Hutus who favored reconciliation with the minority. It also
reignited the civil war.
The panel also will look at the exodus of about 2 million <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Rwanda</ENAMEX>
Hutus to neighboring countries where they lived in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX>-run refugee
camps for 2 1/2 years.
The investigation will consider the role of ``internal and
external forces prior to the genocide and subsequently, and the
role of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Nations</ENAMEX> and its agencies and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">OAU</ENAMEX> before,
during and after the genocide,'' the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">OAU</ENAMEX> said.
The panel will be based in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Addis Ababa</ENAMEX>, and will finish its
investigation within a year, it said. It is to be funded by
voluntary contributions from within and outside the continent.
(aa-kjd)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-OAU-Rwanda; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0813EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

