<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980219.0499 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/19/1998 08:11:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1174 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Denmark-Elections     02-19 0418
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Denmark-Elections </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Prime minister calls March 11 general elections
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">COPENHAGEN</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Denmark</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Poul Nyrup Rasmussen</ENAMEX>
on Thursday made a suprise announcement of national elections to be
held March 11.
	   Although elections were required to be held by September, most
had expected they would be delayed until after the May 28
plebiscite on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">European Union</ENAMEX>'s latest treaty.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nyrup Rasmussen</ENAMEX> interrupted an ordinary parliament session to
announce the elections, saying ``big and important decisions lie
ahead,'' a clear reference to the plebiscite.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Danes</ENAMEX> are known for their lukewarm attitude about <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EU</ENAMEX> membership
and many are concerned that accepting the latest <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EU</ENAMEX> treaty would
require <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Denmark</ENAMEX> to give up too much sovereignty.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nyrup Rasmussen</ENAMEX> said another major topic was to lower the total
government debt of 711.6 billion kroner (dlrs 104.6 4 billion).
	   The government coalition including <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nyrup Rasmussen</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Social
Democratic Party</ENAMEX> and the small center <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Radical Party</ENAMEX> did not resign.
The two groups hold 70 of parliament's 179 seats _ 20 short of the
90 required for majority.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Radical Party</ENAMEX> leader <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marianne Jelved</ENAMEX> told reporters the purpose
of the elections was to ask for voters' support to continue the
government's policy to ``enable us to continue into the next
century.''
	   ``<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Denmark</ENAMEX> today has a stronger economy, a better employment
policy and a more equitable distribution of the benefits than most
other countries in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Europe</ENAMEX>,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nyrup Rasmussen</ENAMEX> said.
	   Unemployment is at 7.4 percent of the labor force _ one of the
lowest in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Europe</ENAMEX> _ and the 1997 growth was of 2.2 percent.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nyrup Rasmussen</ENAMEX> became prime minister in 1993, after a decade
with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Conservative</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Liberal</ENAMEX> governments. His first four-party Cabinet
controlled 90 parliamentary seats and became the first majority
government in more than 20 years.
	   Since then, two parties dropped out, making it a minority
government whose parliamentary survival was assured by a small
center party and two left-wing groups.
	   The prime minister said he would ``be a beast if I didn't say
'yes of course''' about calling the elections now that the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Liberal</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Conservative</ENAMEX> opposition is weak.
	   The Conservatives have been divided by internal fights in almost
a year, while their <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Liberal</ENAMEX> ally has dived slightly in recent
polls.
	   A recent opinion poll indicated the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Social Democrats</ENAMEX> would win
only 56 parliamentary seats _ six less than they currently holds
	   (jo-jh)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Denmark-Elections; CT:i; 
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-19-98 0811EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

