<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980219.0485 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/19/1998 08:05:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1160 &Cx1f; wstm-
u i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Italy-CableCar 1stLd-Writethru   02-19 0561
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Italy-Cable Car, 1st Ld-Writethru </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Italian minister to ask U.S. to give up jurisdiction in cable car
</HEADLINE>
probe &QL; 
 &UR; EDS: UPDATES with comment from Aviano, EDITS to TRIM &QL; 
 &UR; By FRANCES D'EMILIO &QC; 
 &UR; Associated Press Writer &QC; 

<TEXT>
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">ROME</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italian</ENAMEX> government will ask <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> authorities for
jurisdiction in probing the role of the four-man crew of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marine</ENAMEX>
jet which severed a ski gondola cable, Justice Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Giovanni
Maria Flick</ENAMEX> told the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chamber of Deputies</ENAMEX> Thursday.
	   By snapping the cable, the jet, on a training run Feb. 3 from
the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> air base of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Aviano</ENAMEX>, in northeast <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Italy</ENAMEX>, sent the cable car
smashing into a mountain at an <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Alpine</ENAMEX> resort, killing all 20 aboard
the gondola.
	   If <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italy</ENAMEX> receives jurisdiction and decides to indict the crew,
the four could stand trial on charges of multiple manslaughter and
endangering transport.
	   The crew returned safely to base after the accident and
expressed sympathy in a statement to the victim's families.
	   Under <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NATO</ENAMEX>'s 1951 Status of Forces Agreement, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italy</ENAMEX> may make
such a request, and ``the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> will give full consideration'' to
the request, said an <ENAMEX TYPE="FACILITY"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Aviano</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> spokesman, Tech. Sgt. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bill Lincicome</ENAMEX>.
	   But the chances that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> authorities will let the Italians
decide the judicial fate of the crew seemed slim.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lincicome</ENAMEX> noted that there has been no precedent for a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NATO</ENAMEX>
member surrendering jurisdiction in a probe involving the carrying
out of official duty.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italy</ENAMEX>'s request will be made in the next few days via the
foreign <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ministry</ENAMEX>.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italy</ENAMEX> was seeking jurisdiction, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Flick</ENAMEX> told the deputies, given
the gravity of the tragedy and ``the enormous impression on the
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italian</ENAMEX> population, which has shown the strong desire that justice
be carried out in our country.''
	   The request comes at a sensitive time, with some small leftist
parties which support Premier <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Romano Prodi</ENAMEX>'s government opposing
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> use of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italian</ENAMEX> or <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NATO</ENAMEX> bases in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italy</ENAMEX> should there be a strike
against <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Flick</ENAMEX> said the request took into consideration the ``loyal and
reciprocal cooperation between the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italian</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> authorities.''
	   The minister indicated that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italy</ENAMEX> might ask jurisdiction to
probe the role of other Americans attached to <ENAMEX TYPE="FACILITY"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Aviano</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, but that a
final decision hadn't been made on that.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italian</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">American</ENAMEX> militaries are conducting a joint
investigation to determine whether any of the jet's crew or its
commanding officers should face charges.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italian</ENAMEX> civilian prosecutors are conducting a separate
investigation but will be powerless to try the crew unless <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">American</ENAMEX>
authorities give up jurisdiction.
	   On Wednesday, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italian</ENAMEX> news reports said that the jet was well
below its approved altitude when the accident happened.
	   A team of experts appointed by an <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italian</ENAMEX> prosecutor, according
to the news agency <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ANSA</ENAMEX>, contends the EA-6B Prowler sped between
two sets of cables which were 260 feet (85 meters) from the ground
at the lowest point and 400 feet (125 meters) at the highest.
	   The <ENAMEX TYPE="FACILITY"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pentagon</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> has acknowledged that a book used by <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> military
pilots specifically states that pilots in the area where the ski
lift is located were to maintain a minimum altitude of 1,000 feet
(300 meters).
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Flick</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italy</ENAMEX> will advance the compensation for the victims,
with the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX> eventually reimbursing <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italy</ENAMEX> for 75 percent
of the costs.
	   (fd)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Italy-Cable Car, 1st Ld-Writethru; CT:i; 
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-19-98 0805EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

