<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980213.1309 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/13/1998 14:25:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2111 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-DominicanRepublic-US-     02-13 0304
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Dominican Republic-US-Extradition,0309 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Arrest ordered of doctor sought by U.S. in Medicare fraud
</HEADLINE>
&UR; By JOSE P. MONEGRO &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">SANTO DOMINGO</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dominican</ENAMEX> authorities
have arrested a doctor sought by <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> authorities for defrauding
the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Medicare</ENAMEX> system for millions of dollars while practicing in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">New
York</ENAMEX>.
The arrest of the politically well-connected Dr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rafael Gonzalez
Pantaleon</ENAMEX> represents another step by <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dominican</ENAMEX> authorities toward
increased cooperation with the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX>, which is seeking
extradition of numerous suspects hiding out in their home country.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gonzalez Pantaleon</ENAMEX>, a former government official and political
party leader in this <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Caribbean</ENAMEX> nation, was convicted in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">New York</ENAMEX> in
1996 of defrauding <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Medicare</ENAMEX> of dlrs 20 million. He was sentenced to
six and one-half years in prison and fined dlrs 5 million, but he
fled the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX> while free on bail.
Officials said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gonzalez Pantaleon</ENAMEX> was arrested Thursday, one day
after <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> Undersecretary of State <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Hamilton</ENAMEX> met with President
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Leonel Fernandez</ENAMEX> to ask for the extradition of 30 drug trafficking
and murder suspects believed to be in the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>.
Extradition of Dominicans is a controversial topic made more
complicated by conflicting laws. While a 1910 treaty permits
extradition, a law passed in 1969 prohibits Dominicans from being
turned over to other nations. But the latter law did not abolish
the previous treaty.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fernandez</ENAMEX> has urged a new law be passed to clear up the
conflict.
Last year, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fernandez</ENAMEX> handed over to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> authorities two
suspects accused in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> courts of multiple murders, drug
trafficking and conspiracy.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fernandez</ENAMEX> justified the extraditions by saying that the country
could not become a haven for fleeing felons.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Dominican Republic-US-Extradition; CT:i;
(REG:CRB;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-13-98 1425EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

