<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980219.0468 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/19/1998 07:56:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1143 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Georgia-UNKidnappings 2ndLd-Writethru   02-19 0429
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Georgia-UN Kidnappings, 2nd Ld-Writethru </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Four U.N. military observers kidnapped in Georgia
</HEADLINE>
 &UR; Eds: UPDATES with abductors demanding release of those arrested
following attack on president. CLARIFIES in graf 5 that four U.N.
observers were seized along with their Georgian driver, IDENTIFIES
Uruguayan officers in new graf 7. &QL; 
 &UR; By MISHA DZHINDZHIKHASHVILI &QC; 
 &UR; Associated Press Writer &QC; 

<TEXT>
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">TBILISI</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Georgia</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Kidnappers seized four <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Nations</ENAMEX>
military observers in the former <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Soviet</ENAMEX> republic of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Georgia</ENAMEX> on
Thursday, but police quickly tracked down and surrounded the armed
gang.
	   The abductors demanded that the government free seven people
arrested for allegedly taking part in the last week's failed
attempt to kill President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Eduard Shevardnadze</ENAMEX>.
	   Traveling in two cars, the kidnappers abducted the observers and
stole one of their vehicles in the western <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Georgia</ENAMEX> town of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Zugdidi</ENAMEX>,
police said.
	   Several hours later, police encircled a house where the
kidnappers and the hostages were holed up in the village of
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dzhikhaskari</ENAMEX>, 20 kilometers (12 miles) away, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Georgia</ENAMEX>'s Interior
Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kakha Targamadze</ENAMEX> said.
	   Security officials placed armored military vehicles outside the
house and began negotiations with the kidnappers, the interior
minister added.
	   The kidnap victims included two observers from <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Uruguay</ENAMEX>, one from
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Sweden</ENAMEX> and one from the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Czech Republic</ENAMEX>, along with their <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Georgian</ENAMEX>
driver, according to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> office.
	   The Uruguayans were identified as captains <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ronald Garcia</ENAMEX> and
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Julio Navas</ENAMEX>, and the Swede as Maj. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Maaren Moelgaard</ENAMEX>. The identities
of the others were not immediately known.
	   The interior minister said the kidnappers were supporters of
died under mysterious circumstances in 1994.
	   The kidnappers said they would free their hostages only if
authorities release all seven <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gamsakhurdia</ENAMEX> supporters arrested in
recent days for alleged involvement in a Feb. 9 assassination
attempt against <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shevardnadze</ENAMEX>.
	   Two of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shevardnadze</ENAMEX>'s bodyguards were killed in last week's
attack, as was one of the assailants, but the president was
unharmed.
	   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> observers are in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Georgia</ENAMEX> to monitor the truce between
government forces and separatists in the northwest province of
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Abkhazia</ENAMEX>. The separatists took control of the province in a 1992-3
war.
	   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> team, along with <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> forces, have helped prevent
further outbreaks of fighting, but there has been no real progress
toward a political settlement.
	   (md/vi/gm) 	   
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Georgia-UN Kidnappings, 2nd Ld-Writethru; CT:i; 
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-19-98 0756EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

