<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980213.1339 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/13/1998 14:43:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2141 &Cx1f; wstm-
r s &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Sports-Tennis-DavisCu 1stLd-Writethru   02-13 0160
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Sports-Tennis-Davis Cup-Argentina-Colombia, 1st </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Ld-Writethru,0170
</HEADLINE>
&UR; Argentina leads Colombia 2-0 in Davis Cup play &QL;
&UR; Eds: UPDATES with second match, details. &QL;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">BUENOS AIRES</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Argentina</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Franco Squillari</ENAMEX> defeated <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Miguel
Tobon</ENAMEX> 6-2, 6-1, 6-1 on Friday as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Argentina</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> took a 2-0 lead over
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Colombia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> in the first day of Davis Cup competition.
In the opening match, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lucas Arnold</ENAMEX> easily beat <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mario Rincon</ENAMEX> 6-0,
6-2, 6-2 in Group One of the American Zone. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Arnold</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Argentina</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>'s
third-ranking player, needed little more than 1 and 1/2 hours to
finish off <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Colombia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>'s top player.
The competition continues through Sunday at the <ENAMEX TYPE="FACILITY">Mayling Club de
Campo</ENAMEX>, 40 miles (60 kms) north of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Buenos Aires</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lucas Arnold</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Luris Lobo</ENAMEX>, both of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Argentina</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, will face <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Miguel
Tobon</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Philippe Moggio</ENAMEX> in doubles play on Saturday.
If victorious, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Argentina</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> will play <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chile</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> _ whose team includes
recent Australian Open finalist, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marcelo Rios</ENAMEX> _ in April.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Sports-Tennis-Davis Cup-Argentina-Colombia, 1st Ld-Writethru; CT:s;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-13-98 1443EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>


