<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980219.0472 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/19/1998 08:00:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1147 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Portugal-OilSlick     02-19 0327
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Portugal-Oil Slick </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Lisbon port denies entry to leaking oil tanker
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">LISBON</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Portugal</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Portuguese</ENAMEX> navy denied a leaking
crude oil tanker permission to enter port in the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Azores Islands</ENAMEX>
Thursday.
	   The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Singapore</ENAMEX>-registered Front Lord sprung a leak from a cracked
hull Tuesday. By nightfall Wednesday, it was trailing an 800-meter
(yard)slick for 15 kilometers (9.4 miles), <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Portuguese</ENAMEX> navy Cmdr.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Miguel Oliveira</ENAMEX>.
	   ``Only when we have guarantees that the leakage has stopped will
the ship be able to come into port(for repairs),'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Oliveira</ENAMEX> said by
telephone from the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Azores</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="FACILITY">Maritime Rescue Coordination Center</ENAMEX>.
	   The 149,000-ton vessel was in international waters, 250 miles
(400 kilometers) west of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlantic</ENAMEX> archipelago, which lies 1,448
kilometers (900 miles) west of mainland <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Portugal</ENAMEX>.
	   It was carrying almost 264,000 tons of Brent Blend crude and
appeared to be leaking oil from cargo tank number 4, according to a
statement from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Environment Ministry</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Lisbon</ENAMEX>.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Oliveira</ENAMEX> said the ship's crew was working to halt the leak by
transferring the crude from the cracked tank into an empty one.
	   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Environment Ministry</ENAMEX> reported 10-meter (yard)-high waves in
the area and said there was some risk that the tank could split
open, spilling up to 70,000 metric tons of crude into the sea, but
there was no immediate concern of a major spill.
	   ``So far there is no cause for alarm. We are not looking at a
great environmental tragedy,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Environment Ministry</ENAMEX> spokesman
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carlos Pires</ENAMEX> said by telephone.
	   A <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Portuguese</ENAMEX> navy corvette was shadowing the Front Lord but was
not in contact with the vessel, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Oliveira</ENAMEX>.
	   A <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Portuguese</ENAMEX> air force plane left the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Azores</ENAMEX> early Thursday and
was expected to report on the size of the slick later in the day.
	   The ship was heading for the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX>, but <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Oliveira</ENAMEX> had no
details on its exact destination or the crew.
	   (bh/sk/krt)	   
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Portugal-Oil Slick; CT:i; 
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-19-98 0800EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

