<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980213.1329 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/13/1998 14:40:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2131 &Cx1f; wstm-
r s &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Sports-Soccer-Netherl     02-13 0226
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Sports-Soccer-Netherlands-Ajax,0229 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Reports: Ajax planning stock exchange listing
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">AMSTERDAM</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Netherlands</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Storied <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dutch</ENAMEX> soccer club <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ajax
Amsterdam</ENAMEX> is planning to seek a listing on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amsterdam stock
exchange</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dutch</ENAMEX> media reported Friday, citing ``reliable sources.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ajax</ENAMEX> declined comment, but a meeting has been called Monday for
club members to discuss the future, club sources told the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dutch</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NOS</ENAMEX>
and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RTL</ENAMEX> news programs.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ajax</ENAMEX>, currently leading the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dutch</ENAMEX> league and a quarter finalist
in the UEFA Cup, would become the first <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dutch</ENAMEX> soccer club to float
itself on the stock exchange in a move that would likely generate
millions of guilders (dlrs) in extra revenue.
Although <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ajax</ENAMEX> has long been one of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Europe</ENAMEX>'s most successful
clubs, it has never spent heavily on the transfer market, instead
relying on its world famous youth development program to turn out
home-grown stars.
In the past the scheme has produced players including <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johan
Cruyff</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Arsenal</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dennis Bergkamp</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AC Milan</ENAMEX> striker <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Patrick
Kluivert</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ajax</ENAMEX> has won the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dutch</ENAMEX> league a record 26 times and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">European</ENAMEX>
soccer's greatest prize, the European Cup, four times.
Any move to the stock exchange is expected to be led by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ajax</ENAMEX>'s
main sponsor, the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dutch</ENAMEX> bank <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ABN Amro</ENAMEX>. Sources at the bank also
declined to comment on a planned listing.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Sports-Soccer-Netherlands-Ajax; CT:s;
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-13-98 1440EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
