<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980306.1567 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/06/1998 21:32:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2884 &Cx1f; wstm-
r f &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Canada-France-McCain-     03-06 0073
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Canada-France-McCain-Plant,0074 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
McCain to build French french-fry plant
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">FLORENCEVILLE</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">New Brunswick</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">McCain Foods</ENAMEX> plans to build
a major french-fry plant in northeastern <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>.
The dlrs 84-million plant will be located near <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Reims</ENAMEX>, company
chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Harrison McCain</ENAMEX> said Friday. It will employ about 200
people.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">McCain</ENAMEX> said the plant will help meet increasing demand for
french fries in southern <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Canada-France-McCain-Plant; CT:f;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-06-98 2132EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

