<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980219.0505 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/19/1998 08:15:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1181 &Cx1f; wstm-
u i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Greece-Bomb 1stLd-Writethru   02-19 0235
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Greece-Bomb, 1st Ld-Writethru </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Blast damages American car dealership; Iraq protest suspected
</HEADLINE>
 &UR; Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with comments by government
spokesman, U.S. ambassador. No pickup. &QL; 

<TEXT>
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">ATHENS</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Greece</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ A powerful bomb blast Thursday damaged an
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">American</ENAMEX> car dealership in a possible protest to the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> military
confrontation with <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>.
	   The pre-dawn explosion caused heavy damage to the showroom and
offices of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors</ENAMEX> dealership about 12 kilometers (seven
miles) north of central <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Athens</ENAMEX>. There were no injuries.
	   But <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Greek</ENAMEX> media, quoting police sources, said there was
speculation the attack was a protest of possible <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> military
strikes against <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>. The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX> is damanding <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam Hussein</ENAMEX>
give full access to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> weapons inspectors.
to connect the attack with the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> military build-up in the
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Persian Gulf</ENAMEX>.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> Ambassador <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nicholas Burns</ENAMEX>, who met with <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Greek</ENAMEX> police
officials in a pre-scheduled courtesy visit, told reporters that
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> authorities had no direct information on reports that the
blast was linked to the standoff with <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>.
	   There have been a series of bombings around <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Athens</ENAMEX> in recent
months. On Feb. 3, two bombs exploded outside <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">McDonald's</ENAMEX>
restaurants, causing damage but no injuries.
	   bm 	   
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Greece-Bomb, 1st Ld-Writethru; CT:i; 
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:MEST;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-19-98 0815EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

