<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980328.0684 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/28/1998 16:15:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2472 &Cx1f; wstm-
u i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Iraq 4thLd-Writethru   03-28 0616
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Iraq, 4th Ld-Writethru </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Inspectors go near Saddam's hometown for palace searches
</HEADLINE>
&UR; Eds: UPDATES with Saddam visiting northern Iraq &QL;
&UR; AP Photos Available &QL;
&UR; By VIJAY JOSHI &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">BAGHDAD</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Taking their search for weapons of mass
destruction close to President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam Hussein</ENAMEX>'s hometown, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> arms
experts traveled to northern <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Iraq</ENAMEX> Saturday to inspect presidential
palace compounds.
A multinational group of 20 diplomats, mandated by a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>
accord, accompanied the arms experts to the town of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tikrit</ENAMEX>, 25
kilometers (15 miles) west of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Auja</ENAMEX>, the village where <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam</ENAMEX> was
born on April 28, 1937.
``We had no reports of any problems at this stage,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ewen
Buchanan</ENAMEX>, the spokesman for the inspectors, said by telephone from
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">New York</ENAMEX>. ```They will continue with their schedule for the next
week and they are on schedule.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam</ENAMEX> has one palace in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tikrit</ENAMEX>, one at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Jebel Makhul</ENAMEX>, a mountain
range some 50 kilometers (35 miles) north of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tikrit</ENAMEX> and one near
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tharthar lake</ENAMEX>, 50 kilometers (30 miles) southwest of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tikrit</ENAMEX>. It was
not immediately known which one of those the inspectors visited or
how long the inspection lasted.
State-run television on Saturday showed hundreds of villagers
shouting slogans of support for <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam</ENAMEX> as he visited villages near
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tikrit</ENAMEX>.
In a speech, the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraqi</ENAMEX> leader made no mention of the current
searches, which state-run media have also ignored.
The palaces are among the eight that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> had long kept
off-limits from weapons inspectors, citing national sovereignty.
When <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> refused to relent, the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Britain</ENAMEX>
threatened military strikes, raising the specter of war in
February.
Secretary-General <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kofi Annan</ENAMEX> on Feb. 23, pledging to open the
palaces. In return, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Nations</ENAMEX> appointed the group of 20
diplomats to accompany the inspectors to all sensitive sites to
safeguard <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>'s dignity.
The palace inspections began Thursday with the <ENAMEX TYPE="FACILITY">Radwaniyah</ENAMEX>
complex outside <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Baghdad</ENAMEX>. The total area of the eight palace
compounds is 31.5 square kilometers (12.5 square miles), which
comprise 1,058 buildings.
The diplomats and the inspectors in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tikrit</ENAMEX> also are expected to
travel to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Mosul</ENAMEX>, the site of another palace 400 kilometers (235
miles) from <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Baghdad</ENAMEX> during their three-day trip. They will return
to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Baghdad</ENAMEX> on Monday.
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tikrit</ENAMEX>, 170 kilometers (105 miles) from <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Baghdad</ENAMEX>, is the
heartland of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>'s ruling elite, which is dominated by minority
Sunni <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Muslims</ENAMEX>.
Earlier Saturday, the diplomats plus their leader, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jayantha
Dhanapala</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Sri Lanka</ENAMEX>, drove from their downtown hotel to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX>
headquarters to team up with the arms experts at their office
before leaving for the north.
On Friday, a minor surveying problem snagged the inspection but
it was sorted out after talks between the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> team and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraqi</ENAMEX>
Deputy Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tariq Aziz</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Antonio Montiro</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Portuguese</ENAMEX>
diplomat, said.
``Everything went smoothly. Even when we had the problem, we
were able to talk. That's why things were solved,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Montiro</ENAMEX> said.
The inspectors' leader, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">American</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Charles Duelfer</ENAMEX>, stressed that
it wasn't a significant problem.
The inspectors must certify that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> has dismantled its
long-range missile program and its programs to build chemical and
biological weapons before the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Security Council</ENAMEX> will consider
lifting the economic sanctions it imposed after <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>'s 1990
invasion of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Kuwait</ENAMEX>. The sanctions have strangled <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>'s economy.
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> has insisted that has complied with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> resolutions
and that any banned weapons have been destroyed and the programs to
build them abolished.
</TEXT>
&UR; vj-lm
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Iraq, 4th Ld-Writethru; CT:i;
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-28-98 1615EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

