<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980227.0476 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 08:02:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2381 &Cx1f; wstm-
u i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-WorldCourt-Lockerbie 5thLd   02-27 0169
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-World Court-Lockerbie, 5th Ld </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
World Court declares jurisdiction in Lockerbie dispute
</HEADLINE>
&UR; Eds: RECASTS lead to clarify; ADDS detail of U.S. and British
objections in 3rd graf. &QL;
&UR; AP Photo staffing &QL;
&UR; By MIKE CORDER &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">THE HAGUE</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Netherlands</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">World Court</ENAMEX> Friday rejected
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">British</ENAMEX> objections to a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Libyan</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">World Court</ENAMEX> case that has
blocked the trial of two Libyans suspected of blowing up a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pan Am</ENAMEX>
jumbo jet over <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Scotland</ENAMEX> in 1988.
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Libya</ENAMEX>, which brought the case to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Nations</ENAMEX>' highest
judicial body in its dispute with the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Britain</ENAMEX>,
hailed the ruling and said it would press anew for a trial in a
third neutral country.
Both <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">British</ENAMEX> officials filed objections to the court's
jurisdiction in 1995, claiming <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Security Council</ENAMEX> resolutions imposed
on <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Lybia</ENAMEX> to force the suspects' extradition overruled a 1971
Convention which gives <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Libya</ENAMEX> the right to try the men.
The decision, 3rd graf pvs.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-World Court-Lockerbie, 5th Ld; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0802EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

