<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980227.0488 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 08:10:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2393 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Spain-Accident     02-27 0160
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Spain-Accident </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
British man dies with four Spaniards in traffic accident
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">SEVILLE</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Spain</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ A <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">British</ENAMEX> man was among five people killed
in a car crash on the main road connecting the southern <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Spanish</ENAMEX>
cities of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Seville</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Malaga</ENAMEX>, police said Friday.
Police identified the dead Britain only by the initials <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">R.D.F.P</ENAMEX>,
but news reports said his full name was <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roy Dermott Fitzpatrick</ENAMEX>,
originally from <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ashby-de-la-Zouch</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Leicestershire</ENAMEX> and a resident
of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Balearic Islands</ENAMEX> off the eastern <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Spanish</ENAMEX> mainland.
Police said the 31-year-old Britain died late Thursday along
with three Spaniards, two women and one man, when their Ford Escort
was collided into by an Opel Astra driven by a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Spanish</ENAMEX> male who
also died.
The authorities have yet to determine whether the five victims
died instantaneously in the crash or in the flames that enveloped
the two vehicles shortly afterwards, police said.
(jt)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Spain-Accident; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0810EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

