<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980428.0729 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 04/28/1998 10:48:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1672 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-EU-CreditLyonnais     04-28 0337
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-EU-Credit Lyonnais </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Credit Lyonnais workers protest against EU demands
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">BRUSSELS</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Belgium</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) - Some 2,500 <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Lyonnais</ENAMEX> employees
demonstrated Tuesday outside <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">European Union</ENAMEX> headquarters to protest
against conditions the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">EU</ENAMEX> wants to impose on <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">French</ENAMEX> government
subsidies to the troubled state bank.
Union representatives met with officials of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EU Commission</ENAMEX>.
After several hours, they walked out saying talks had been
completely unproductive.
``The Commission won't budge,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Georges Begot</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CFDT</ENAMEX>
union. ``There is still some room for negotiation but it seems very
limited.''
The Commission has powers to veto or impose conditions on
government subsidies if it judges they distort fair competition
within the 15-nation bloc.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">EU</ENAMEX> executive wants <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Lyonnais</ENAMEX> to sell off all <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">European</ENAMEX>
assets outside <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> and reduce its <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">French</ENAMEX> network. The Commission
says the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">French</ENAMEX> government should sell the bank to the best bidder
by the end of 1999.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">French</ENAMEX> government and the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">EU</ENAMEX> have been battling for years
over billions of francs (dollars) aid given to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Lyonnais</ENAMEX>
since the bank incurred heavy losses in the 1980s.
Last month, the bank reported net profits of 1.1 billion <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">French</ENAMEX>
francs (dlrs 180 million) in 1997. But the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">EU</ENAMEX>'s top competition
watchdog, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Karel Van Miert</ENAMEX>, said the results contained an illegal
government subsidy of more than 3 billion francs (dlrs 490
million.)
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">French</ENAMEX> Finance Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dominique Strauss-Kahn</ENAMEX> said last week
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> will sell <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Lyonnais</ENAMEX> by the end of next year.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Lyonnais</ENAMEX> has shed several thousand jobs over the past 10
years, but still employs 32,000 people. The protesters blamed job
losses on <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">EU</ENAMEX> interference.
``<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> is paying (for the bank). Why does the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">EU</ENAMEX> have to
interfere?'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marie-Claude Latte</ENAMEX>, who has worked at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit
Lyonnais</ENAMEX> for 28 years.
``We've made sacrifices: we've had to accept longer working
hours and less money,'' she added, waving one of her paychecks.
</TEXT>
&UR; (as-pa)
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-EU-Credit Lyonnais; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-04-28-98 1048EDT
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

