<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980304.0327 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/04/1998 06:41:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1676 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Pakistan-Execution     03-04 0145
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Pakistan-Execution,0144 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Man hanged in eastern Pakistan for double murder
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">LAHORE</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Pakistan</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Maqsood Kalia</ENAMEX>, whose murder convictions
were questioned by <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Lahore</ENAMEX>'s police chief, was hanged Wednesday in
the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Punjab</ENAMEX> capital of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Lahore</ENAMEX>.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lahore High Court</ENAMEX> sentenced <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kalia</ENAMEX> to death last year for the
shooting deaths of two people in 1996.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kalia</ENAMEX> appealed the verdict, and during the second trial <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Lahore</ENAMEX>
Police Chief <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mubasher Ahmed</ENAMEX> testified that he believed <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kalia</ENAMEX> was
innocent. The court rejected <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ahmed</ENAMEX>'s testimony, saying the police
chief had no evidence to back his claim.
President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rafiq Tarar</ENAMEX> on Tuesday rejected an appeal for clemency
filed by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kalia</ENAMEX>'s mother, authorities said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kalia</ENAMEX> was hanged inside <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Lahore</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="FACILITY">Kot Lakbhat Jail</ENAMEX>, prison
officials said. His body was later given to his family, who waited
outside the prison compound.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Pakistan-Execution; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-04-98 0641EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

