<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980305.1201 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/05/1998 14:15:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2521 &Cx1f; wstm-
r s &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Sports-Soccer-WorldCu 1stLd-Writethru   03-05 0516
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Sports-Soccer-World Cup-Iran-US, 1st Ld-Writethru,0516 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Tight schedule forces Iran to turn down friendly with America
</HEADLINE>
&UR; EDS: UPDATES with U.S. comment; Stands as 2nd Ld-Writethru to some
lines to identify Gulati as USSF vice president, add more detail. &QL;
&UR; By AFSHIN VALINEJAD &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">TEHRAN</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iran</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iran</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> has declined an invitation from the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Soccer Federation</ENAMEX> to play a friendly match in the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United
States</ENAMEX>, an <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iranian</ENAMEX> soccer official said Thursday.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mohsen Safai Farahani</ENAMEX>, the president of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iran</ENAMEX>'s football
federation, said the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USSF</ENAMEX> sent a fax about two weeks ago, inviting
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iran</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> to come to the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX> ``in an all-expenses paid trip to
meet the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> team in a friendly match.''
``Unfortunately, and because our program is fully booked and
because of the long distance, we thanked them and turned the
invitation down,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Farahani</ENAMEX> told reporters.
However, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USSF</ENAMEX> vice president and deputy commissioner of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S.
Major League Soccer</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sunil Gulati</ENAMEX> said Thursday that the invitation
was for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iran</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> to play <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Mexico</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, not the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United States</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.
``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Mexico</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> wants to play some <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Asian</ENAMEX> teams because they have <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">South
Korea</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> in their group,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gulati</ENAMEX> said.
Since <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Mexico</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> on occasion plays in the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX>, often to
reach their heavy support in Southern California, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USSF</ENAMEX> acted on
behalf of the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Mexican</ENAMEX> federation in sending out invitation letters
to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">South Korea</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iran</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">China</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gulati</ENAMEX> also approached <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Japan</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> verbally, he said.
Also attending the press conference was <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Croatian</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> coach <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tomislav
Ivic</ENAMEX>, who took over the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iranian</ENAMEX> team from <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Brazilian</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Valdir Vierra</ENAMEX>
after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iran</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> claimed the last spot in the 32-team World Cup field in
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> in June.
``It would have been a fantastic opportunity and we would've
liked to go there but our schedule was complete and we couldn't
change it,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ivic</ENAMEX> said.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United States</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iran</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> are grouped together along with
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Germany</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Yugoslavia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> for the first round of the World Cup.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ivic</ENAMEX> said the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iranian</ENAMEX> team will travel to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> next week to
play against first division teams <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Montpellier</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Nantes</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> before
returning to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tehran</ENAMEX> for friendly matches against <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Hungary</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ghana</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Jamaica</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ivic</ENAMEX> downplayed the importance of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iran</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>'s World Cup match with
the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United States</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.
``We want to qualify to the second round. This is our first
wish. All three games are different and we need to prepare special
tactics for each one. Each game is important,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ivic</ENAMEX> said.
He said the roster for the finals was not complete and he was
awaiting a number of players to join the camp after finishing their
club duty.
Some 15 players, who form the backbone of the national team, are
from <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iran</ENAMEX>'s two major clubs, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Esteqlal</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Piroozi</ENAMEX>. Both teams are
currently engaged in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Asian</ENAMEX> championships.
Despite the risk of losing one or more of the players to injury,
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Farahani</ENAMEX> said he was happy that the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Esteqlal</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Piroozi</ENAMEX> players
were competing in regional competitions.
``We believe that playing in the league and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Asian</ENAMEX> tournaments
will create the best situation for the national team,'' he said.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Sports-Soccer-World Cup-Iran-US, 1st Ld-Writethru; CT:s;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-05-98 1415EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

