<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980319.0652 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/19/1998 10:14:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2931 &Cx1f; wstm-
r s &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Sports-Soccer-Spanish     03-19 0442
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Sports-Soccer-Spanish Preview,0441 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Jubilant Barcelona looks to consolidate seven-point lead
</HEADLINE>
&UR; By CIARAN GILES &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">MADRID</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Spain</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ With just 10 rounds remaining, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FC Barcelona</ENAMEX>
lies a comfortable seven points ahead of nearest challenger <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Real
Madrid</ENAMEX> as it takes on an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Athletic Bilbao</ENAMEX> gunning for a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UEFA</ENAMEX> cup
berth.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Barcelona</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> goes into the 30th-round game Sunday still buoyant
after its 3-0 victory over <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Real Madrid</ENAMEX> two weeks ago which it
followed up with by winning the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">European</ENAMEX> Supercup in a victory over
European Champions Cup semifinalist <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Borussia Dortmund</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Louis Van Gaal</ENAMEX>'s crew then stretched its lead over eternal rival
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Madrid</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> to seven points last round when it narrowly defeated
weakling side <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compostela</ENAMEX> 2-1.
Its opponent Sunday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bilbao</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, downed <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Mallorca</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> 3-1 last round to
edge up to sixth place in the 20-team division, with 47 points, 11
less than <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Barcelona</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.
``We'll go to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Barcelona</ENAMEX> with no hang-ups,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bilbao</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> defender
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Aitor Larazabal</ENAMEX>. ``We already know what it's like to beat them and
now we must try to win every game so as not to lose out in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UEFA</ENAMEX>.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Barcelona</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> will be without <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Spanish</ENAMEX> international right back
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Albert Ferrer</ENAMEX> because of supsension.
Meanwhile, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Madrid</ENAMEX> takes on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Barcelona</ENAMEX>'s last victim, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Compostela</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>,
in its 30th-round game also Sunday. The side is certain to be
overflowing with confidence in the aftermath of the 3-0 drubbing of
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bayer Leverkusen</ENAMEX> Wednesday that advanced it into the semifinals of
the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">European</ENAMEX> Champions Cup.
``It was the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Madrid</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> that all of us wanted to see,'' said
chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lorenzo Sanz</ENAMEX>.
The result came as a welcome breather for <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">German</ENAMEX> coach <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Juup
Heynckes</ENAMEX> whose future at the club had been questioned following
dismal domestic league performances, and particularly after the
humiliating defeat by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Barcelona</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.
A defeat for <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Madrid</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> on Sunday, however, would be fatal for the
side's already slim chances of catching the leader and could lead
to renewed pressure on <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Heynckes</ENAMEX>.
New surprise team <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Celta</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, third with 48 points, travels to
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Mallorca</ENAMEX> hoping to extend its seven-match unbeaten streak.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Real Sociedad</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Betis</ENAMEX>, both with 47 points, face each other in
a battle for fourth place with both teams determined to keep their
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UEFA</ENAMEX> Cup hopes alive.
In the league's only game Saturday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Atletico Madrid</ENAMEX>, triumphant
after its UEFA quarterfinal victory midweek, travels to lowly
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Salamanca</ENAMEX>.
Other 30th-round games Sunday are: <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Valencia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> vs. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Espanyol</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>;
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deportivo de La Coruna</ENAMEX> vs. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Zaragoza</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sporting de Gijon</ENAMEX> vs. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Merida</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>;
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tenerife</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> vs <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Oviedo</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>; and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Racing de Santander</ENAMEX> vs.<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Valladolid</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.
No game is scheduled for Monday.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Sports-Soccer-Spanish Preview; CT:s;
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-19-98 1014EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

