<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980219.0516 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/19/1998 08:18:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1192 &Cx1f; wstm-
u i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Palestinians-Iraq 4thLd-Writethru   02-19 0481
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Palestinians-Iraq, 4th Ld-Writethru </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Police fire in the air to disperse pro-Iraq march
</HEADLINE>
 &UR; Eds: UPDATES with Palestinian police blocking a pro-Iraq rally in
the West Bank town of Ramallah, in 10th graf &QL; 
 &UR; By NASSER SHIYOUKHI &QC; 
 &UR; Associated Press Writer &QC; 

<TEXT>
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">DURA</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Bank</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israeli</ENAMEX> policemen fired live rounds in
the air Thursday to disperse hundreds of young Palestinians who
blocked a major <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Bank</ENAMEX> road to show their support for <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam
Hussein</ENAMEX>.
	   The confrontation began when elementary and high school students
marched and burned <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israeli</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> flags in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dura</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Bank</ENAMEX> town
that remains under <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israeli</ENAMEX> security control.
	   At one point, the marchers blocked the main road running through
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dura</ENAMEX> with boulders, and hurled rocks at an <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israeli</ENAMEX> police van and
settler cars. The four policemen in the van called for backup and
then fired in the air with pistols and assault rifles.
	   Three more vans and an <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israeli</ENAMEX> army jeep arrived a few minutes
later. There were no immediate reports of injury.
	   After a while, the shooting stopped and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israeli</ENAMEX> soldiers began
firing tear gas and rubber bullets at the demonstrators. Troops
chased stone throwers into the fields. Two Palestinians were
injured by rubber bullets and six were overcome by tear gas.
	   The incident marked the most serious confrontation between
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israeli</ENAMEX> troops and Palestinians since pro-<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> demonstrations began
in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Bank</ENAMEX> several weeks ago.
	   The rallies often ended in stone throwing clashes, but until now
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israeli</ENAMEX> troops have fired only rubber bullets, not live ammunition.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Palestinian Authority</ENAMEX> has banned pro-<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> rallies, but that ban
has been widely ignored.
	   The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Palestinian Authority</ENAMEX> has also prohibited <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Palestinian</ENAMEX> radio
and television stations from broadcasting commentary in support of
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam</ENAMEX> or footage of demonstrations. The ban came under pressure
from the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX>.
	   <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Palestinian</ENAMEX> leader <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yasser Arafat</ENAMEX>, who paid a heavy price for his
open support of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam</ENAMEX> during the 1991 Gulf War, has been carefully
neutral in his statements, saying he would like to see a diplomatic
solution to the conflict.
	   In the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Bank</ENAMEX> town of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ramallah</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Palestinian</ENAMEX> police prevented
a planned pro-<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> rally by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Palestinian Professionals' Union</ENAMEX>.
Police told organizers they would be breaking the law if they went
ahead and the marchers left quietly.
	   The march in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dura</ENAMEX> began Thursday morning with about 800 school
students waving <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraqi</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Palestinian</ENAMEX> flags and urging <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam
Hussein</ENAMEX> to fire missiles at <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israel</ENAMEX>.
	   ``With our spirit and our blood, we will redeem <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>,'' and
``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam</ENAMEX>, our beloved, hit <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tel Aviv</ENAMEX>,'' shouted the about
800 elementary and high school students.
	   Demonstrators burned six <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israeli</ENAMEX> and two <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S</ENAMEX>. flags and several
held up a banner reading ``Why do the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraqi</ENAMEX> people have to pay the
price for <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Clinton</ENAMEX>'s affairs?''
</TEXT>
 &UR; ns/ga-kl
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Palestinians-Iraq, 4th Ld-Writethru; CT:i; 
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-19-98 0818EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

