<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980322.0749 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/22/1998 14:57:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1834 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-NorthernIreland 1stLd-Writethru   03-22 0720
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Northern Ireland, 1st Ld-Writethru </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Police find bomb on eve of Sinn Fein's return to peace talks
</HEADLINE>
&UR; Eds: NEW throughout; RAISES reference to bomb; UPDATES with protest
against Protestant marches, comment from Sinn Fein leader; trims
pvs &QL;
&UR; By SHAWN POGATCHNIK &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">BELFAST</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Northern Ireland</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Police seized a car bomb under
construction Sunday in a town bordering <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Northern Ireland</ENAMEX> on the eve
of the return to peace talks by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IRA</ENAMEX>-allied <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sinn Fein</ENAMEX> party.
Chief Superintendent <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Al McHugh</ENAMEX> said the bomb discovered in the
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Irish Republic</ENAMEX> was destined for an unknown target in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Northern
Ireland</ENAMEX> and ``would have caused massive destruction.''
The discovery appeared to be the latest attempt by extremists
opposed to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IRA</ENAMEX>'s 8-month-old truce to undermine the peace
process, set to resume Monday in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Belfast</ENAMEX>.
Extremists have bombed two predominantly pro-<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">British</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Protestant</ENAMEX>
towns and fired mortar shells at a police station since <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sinn Fein</ENAMEX>
was expelled from peace talks on Feb. 20 in punishment for two
killings blamed on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Irish Republican Army</ENAMEX>.
Police found more than 1,300 pounds (600 kgs) of
fertilizer-based explosives Sunday in a shed in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dundalk</ENAMEX>, 50 miles
(80 kms) south of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Belfast</ENAMEX>.
They arrested two men in connection with the bomb factory, which
also contained circuitry, detonating cord and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi</ENAMEX> truck
that would have carried the bomb.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">British</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Irish</ENAMEX> governments, which cosponsor the
multi-party talks that are supposed to conclude by May, invited
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sinn Fein</ENAMEX> to rejoin two weeks ago.
But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sinn Fein</ENAMEX> leader <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gerry Adams</ENAMEX> kept his party out pending
meetings with <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">British</ENAMEX> Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tony Blair</ENAMEX> 10 days ago and
President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Clinton</ENAMEX> last week.
``We were unjustly pushed out of the talks in February but we
are back,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Adams</ENAMEX> said Sunday.
He said the north's substantial <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Catholic</ENAMEX> minority demanded a
settlement that would promote <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Northern Ireland</ENAMEX>'s eventual
unification with the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Irish Republic</ENAMEX>.
``Nationalists in the north are not a minority in someone else's
country. We are <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Irish</ENAMEX> citizens, living in our own country,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Adams</ENAMEX>
said, adding: ``Nationalists want to move towards <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Irish</ENAMEX> unity and
see this process as a bridge in that direction.''
But the north's pro-<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">British</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Protestant</ENAMEX> majority is bitterly
opposed to uniting <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ireland</ENAMEX> and instead wants a strong government
for <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Northern Ireland</ENAMEX>, which has been ruled directly by <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">London</ENAMEX> since
1972.
Unionists</ENAMEX>, is threatening to push for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sinn Fein</ENAMEX>'s expulsion once
again. They say <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IRA</ENAMEX> commanders are responsible for the recent bomb
attacks.
Also Sunday, more than 2,000 <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Catholic</ENAMEX> protesters rallied in
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Portadown</ENAMEX> against the annual parades by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Orange Order</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Northern
Ireland</ENAMEX>'s dominant <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Protestant</ENAMEX> fraternal group.
Confrontations among <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Catholic</ENAMEX> protesters, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Protestant</ENAMEX> marchers
and the police have provoked widespread violence in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Northern
Ireland</ENAMEX> for the past three summers. The crucible is <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Portadown</ENAMEX>, 30
miles (50 kms) southwest of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Belfast</ENAMEX>, where Orangemen march each
July from their rural church back downtown _ through the town's
main <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Catholic</ENAMEX> area.
Protesters from several <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Catholic</ENAMEX> communities crowded into
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Portadown</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Catholic</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="FACILITY">Garvaghy Road</ENAMEX> to hear speakers demand
negotiations with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Orange Order</ENAMEX> leaders, and pledge to participate
in each others' road-blocking protests this summer.
``Small nationalist communities are not going to be left on
their own this summer,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gerard Rice</ENAMEX>, a former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IRA</ENAMEX> prisoner
who leads anti-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Orange</ENAMEX> protests in a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Catholic</ENAMEX> neighborhood of south
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Belfast</ENAMEX>.
Riot police in armored cars, shields and helmets prevented a few
hundred Protestants, many waving <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">British</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ulster</ENAMEX> flags, from
interfering with the Catholics as they marched within <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Portadown</ENAMEX>'s
few <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Catholic</ENAMEX> streets.
Earlier Sunday, police and militant Protestants clashed in a
religiously polarized part of north <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Belfast</ENAMEX>.
Police said an unmarked police car was hit with gasoline bombs
from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Protestant</ENAMEX> side. Riot police responded with a volley of
plastic bullets that scattered a 50-strong mob.
An elderly <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Catholic</ENAMEX> man was hospitalized from cuts after a
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Protestant</ENAMEX> gasoline bomb landed in his back yard. Police arrested
six Protestants on suspicion of rioting.
(sp/eml)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Northern Ireland, 1st Ld-Writethru; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-22-98 1457EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

