<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980409.0349 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 04/09/1998 07:41:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1215 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Netherlands-DeathPena     04-09 0249
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Netherlands-Death Penalty </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Study reveals growing Dutch support for death penalty
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">AMSTERDAM</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Netherlands</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Dutch</ENAMEX> support for the death
penalty is growing with a majority in favor of imposing it for
serious crimes, including incest and child abuse, a new study
shows.
According to the latest survey of 3,000 people, one in two
participants, or 52 percent, supports the death penalty, which was
abolished in the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Netherlands</ENAMEX> in 1870.
In previous surveys, support ranged between 40 and 45 percent.
Survey investigator Dr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Karin Wittebrood</ENAMEX> said Thursday it is
difficult to establish what had triggered the increase, but timing
may have been a factor.
The study was conducted during the latter part of 1996 when
publicity over the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marc Dutroux</ENAMEX> child-murder case in neighboring
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Belgium</ENAMEX> reached its height and public concerns spilled over the
border.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wittebrood</ENAMEX> said many of those who support the death penalty said
it should be imposed for murder, incest and child abuse.
Although the rise reflects a significant change in public
opinion, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wittebrood</ENAMEX> believes the change is only temporary in this
tolerant country.
The survey also showed that supporters of the death penalty are
mostly young people or those with a low level of education.
The survey, carried out by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Netherlands Institute for the
Study of Crime and Law Enforcement</ENAMEX>, was conducted via face-to-face
interviews. Its margin of error was not disclosed.
(jc/bk)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Netherlands-Death Penalty; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-04-09-98 0741EDT
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

