<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980401.1133 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 04/01/1998 13:01:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2546 &Cx1f; wstm-
r w &Cx13;  &Cx11;  WHERE-MONEY-GROWSsked     04-01 1822
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> WHERE-MONEY-GROWS sked </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
MALAYSIA
</HEADLINE>
&QL;
xfdws WHERE-MONEY-GROWS sked
Emerging Markets Datafile
January 16, 1998
INVESTOR DIGEST
ENGLISH
<TEXT>
AS <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Asian</ENAMEX> currencies grapple with their diminished value, foreign
exchange (forex) dealers are scurrying around to take long positions
in the currencies of developed nations, particularly the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">US</ENAMEX> Dollar and
the Pound Sterling.
The enthusiasm comes at a time when most currencies in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Asia</ENAMEX>, from
industrialised countries like <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Japan</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">South Korea</ENAMEX> right down to
developing nations like <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Indonesian</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Malaysia</ENAMEX> suffered a 30% to 40%
defacto devaluation across the board.
Forex and currency trading, quite lackadaisical particularly in the
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">South East Asian</ENAMEX> region in last few years, escalated tremendously
somewhere in the middle of this year as currency attacks swept across
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Asia</ENAMEX>, putting many of its economies in dire straits.
`The safest and highest returns in currency investments for next year,
based on the current circumstances are the greenback and the Pound
Sterling. They have low risks and and considerably good interest and
capital gains,' says a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Kuala Lumpur</ENAMEX>-based forex dealer.  The stellar
position of these two currencies are attributed to the steady growth
rates in the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United States</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United Kingdom</ENAMEX>, compared with the
figures seen in the rest of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Europe</ENAMEX> and other developed nations like
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Japan</ENAMEX>.
The latter recently admitted that its economic growth has stalled and
it would virtually be impossible for the country to grow at even one
per cent for this year.
The dealer adds that although interest rates in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Southeast Asia</ENAMEX> are on
an upward trend, culminating from the currency depreciation, the
currencies of this region hold a high risk premium associated with the
uncertainties that shroud the region.
`At the moment, most people are adopting a defensive trading strategy.
Although interest yields in the regional currencies are better than
those in the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Unites States</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United Kingdom</ENAMEX>, the risk factor is more
pronounced due to the instability,' says another dealer.  The risk he
is refering to is a lower capital yield if the currencies were to
depreciate. If the fall in value is substantial, the interest gain
could be wiped out by the capital losses.  However, not all market
observers will vouch for the performance of the greenback and Pound
Sterling next year. A treasurer in a local bank says that next year is
going to be rather complicated.  In 1998, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">European Monetary Union
(<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EMU</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX> will decide which countries in the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">European Union (<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">EU</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX> will
qualify for its single currency unit, Euro, due to be launched in
January 1999.  He points out that there will be a lot of speculation
as the currency scrambles to find its true value.
The dilemma now is how the Euro will be received in the market and its
effect on the Pound Sterling, which was ousted from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EMU</ENAMEX> after it
took a severe beating in 1992. The treasurer believes that if there is
more interest shown in the single currency, the Pound Sterling may
start losing ground and find its strength faltering.  However, there
are several uncertainties that need to be ironed out first. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EMU</ENAMEX>
will have to determine who will participate in the euro. To conserve
the currency's strength, one criterion is that inflation in the
individual <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">EU</ENAMEX> countries should not exceed 1.5 percentage points above
the three best performing nations. To date, six countries qualify.
Then, there is the question of conversion rates from individual
currencies to the euro. For instance, the Franc may have a different
conversion rate to the euro compared with the Deutche Mark. All of
this will ultimately determine the trading volatility in the euro.
As the single unit comes into being, there may be high volatility in
the individual <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">European</ENAMEX> currencies market. The market's reaction
depends on a slew of factors and if it is sceptical about the
implementation of the euro, heavy trading will find the value of the
continent's currencies eroding.  `However, there will not be very much
impact for the time being as the euro, upon its inception, will have
limited usage,' says a trader. In the initial stages, the currency
will be mainly utilised as a currency exchange mechanism rather than a
monetary unit's conventional role as the tool for the exchange for
goods and services.
Another trader has his reservations about the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">US</ENAMEX> Dollar's performance
in1998. `The Dow Jones is currently buoyant and many predict that the
bubble may burst next year,' he says. Trading at above 8,000 points,
some analysts see the 25 times Price-Earnings Ratio (PER) of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New
York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NYSE</ENAMEX>), with certain individual counters exceeding
30 times, is seen as a sign of an overvalued market.
`When the chips start falling down, you will see the Dollar losing its
grip because of a possible capital flight from the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">US</ENAMEX>,' says a
locally-based trader. He adds that this may mean that funds will find
its way back to this region, giving its currencies a lift.  What is
the Ringgit's outlook like in 1998? Money market observers and
economists interviewed by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Investors Digest</ENAMEX> believe the Ringgit's
rebound will not solely depend on the developments at home, but also
those in the entire <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Asian</ENAMEX> region. This is because the restoration of
foreign investors' confidence in these markets will work wonders for
their currencies.
They agree that the Ringgit's depreciation vis-a-vis major currencies
across the board is a spinoff from the current events that occured in
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Asia</ENAMEX>. `We are affected by our neighbours,' says one observer.
Indeed, the recent state of affairs enveloping the financial sectors
of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Japan</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">South Korea</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Indonesia</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX> has a rippling effect on
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Malaysia</ENAMEX>.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Asian</ENAMEX> turmoil has claimed a number of unexpected victims,
including <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Japan</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Yamaichi Securities</ENAMEX>, the country's fourth largest
broking house.
Besides that, six merchant banks in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">South Korea</ENAMEX> and 56 financial
institutions in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX> were closed. <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">South Korea</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX> and
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Indonesia</ENAMEX> are currently being assisted by an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Monetary
Fund</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IMF</ENAMEX>) rescue package.  These developments have a major effect on
the Ringgit's prospects.
`There will be a slight improvement in the Ringgit, provided the dust
in the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Asian</ENAMEX> region settles. If it doesn't, for instance, if the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IMF</ENAMEX>
bailout fails, then we can expect another wave of attacks on the
currency,' an economist elucidates.
Although most observers are not very bullish about the Ringgit's
performance in 1998, they believe it will fare better than it did this
year mainly because it is presently undervalued. The currency is
currently trading at a range of RM3.60 to RM3.70 against the
greenback. Says one observer, `It is even possible for the Ringgit to
go down temporarily to RM4.00, but it will surge again soon after.'He
adds that 1998 will be a year of consolidation for the currency. Most
observers opine that the Ringgit's fair value should be somewhere in
the region of RM3.00 to RM3.50 against the greenback, taking into
account trade figures and the overall weakness in the regional
economies.
As for 1997, the Ringgit's high was about RM2.465 in January and a
historical low of RM3.885 in December, vis-a-vis the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">US</ENAMEX> Dollar.  Our
local unit however rebounded sharply to RM3.723 after Deputy Prime
Minister and Finance Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Datuk Seri Anwar Ibrahim</ENAMEX> announced a
spate of additional austerity measures to address the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Malaysian</ENAMEX>
economic problems. It has risen further to breach the RM3.65 level.
Will the currency continue to track this upward movement into 1998? A
market observer believed that the rally took place because of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Anwar</ENAMEX>'s
announcements and the funds went back to the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Malaysian</ENAMEX> market.
However, analysts point out the fact that the belt-tightening measures
and the revised Gross Domestic Product (GDP) rate to about four to
five per cent in 1998 will slow down the country's growth.  Companies
with a high exposure to the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">US</ENAMEX> Dollar, like <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tenaga Nasional Bhd</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TNB</ENAMEX>),
will see their profits coming down.  Says a forex dealer, `Some
multinationals have announced that they will cut production due to
high costs and with reduced foreign direct investments (FDI), the
Ringgit will probably remain at the RM3.60 to RM3.70 level.'However,
factors such as the Commonwealth Games to be held in September next
year can provide a temporary boost to the currency. `When tourists
flock the country for the games, their expenditure here will create
demand for the Ringgit, and we will see the currency appreciating,' he
says.  However, how substantial the Ringgit's value increases will
depend on the quantum of demand created for it.  An economist in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Kuala
Lumpur</ENAMEX> points out that any positive implications from the games will
only be reflected in the third or fourth quarter of the year. `It may
not be substantive enough to outweigh the overall weakness in the
Ringgit throughout the year, as the Commonwealth Games is a one-off
event,' he adds.  He believes that next year, the Ringgit should trade
at the RM3.20 to RM3.50 level to remain competitive. `If the Ringgit
appreciates to this level, it will be good because it helps to cushion
off import bills and will not hit our exports,' he explains.  As other
currencies in the region have also depreciated, a sharp rise in the
Ringgit could impede <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Malaysia</ENAMEX>'s exports.  What role can interest rates
play in the Ringgit's value? Very little, according
analysts. Traditionally, interest rates in a country are hiked to
support an ailing currency by attracting short-term capital.
However, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Southeast Asian</ENAMEX> region has bucked the trend.  `Interest
rates in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Indonesia</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX> have risen significantly but their
currencies are still weak because there is not enough investor
confidence,' says a treasurer in a foreign bank.  In <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Malaysia</ENAMEX>,
interest rates are currently at 9.09% while the base lending rate
(BLR) has jumped up over three basis points to be in the region of
more than 10%. These hikes are not used as a tool to shore up the
Ringgit's value but instead to curb inflation and credit growth.
Besides, interest rates tend to rise in an environment with a general
shortage of funds.
The Ringgit's performance in 1998 hinges greatly on the stability of
the regional currencies and the fate of the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">European</ENAMEX> currencies and
the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">US</ENAMEX> Dollar. As one analyst puts it, `The Ringgit will definitely
pull through when there is more investors' confidence in the region.
</TEXT>
Copyright 1998 INVESTOR DIGEST all rights reserved as
distributed by World Sources Online, Inc.
(PROFILE
(WS SL:WHERE-MONEY-GROWS sked; CT:w;
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-04-01-98 1301EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
