<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980311.1357 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/11/1998 15:02:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2104 &Cx1f; wstm-
r s &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Sports-Cycling-Tirren 1stLd-Writethru   03-11 0307
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Sports-Cycling-Tirreno-Adriatico, 1st Ld-Writethru,0306 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Italian wins opening stage; Ullrich withdraws
</HEADLINE>
&UR; EDS: CORRECTS mileage conversions. &QL;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">SORRENTO</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italy</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ The season debut of Tour of France winner
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jan Ullrich</ENAMEX> was short-lived Wednesday as the flu-weakened German
withdrew during the opening stage of the Tirreno-Adriatico race.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ullrich</ENAMEX>, who stopped pedaling one hour into the race, said he
was confident he would recover his health and form by the start of
the Milan-to-San Remo classic _ the first race of the 1998 World
Cup scheduled along the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Italian Riviera</ENAMEX> on March 21.
Young <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italian</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gabriele Balducci</ENAMEX> took the first of eight stages
of the Tirreno-Adriatico _ a 133-kilometer (83-mile) circuit around
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Sorrento</ENAMEX> _ outsprinting the pack at the finish line.
A five-second bonus from the stage victory also gave <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Balducci</ENAMEX>
the overall leadership. Despite the double victory, the Italian was
unhappy with narrow roads and slippery asphalt, and had a public
argument with the race organizers.
The stage was marred by several spills. The most serious, in the
final kilometers, sent <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italian</ENAMEX> cyclist <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Paolo Bettini</ENAMEX> to the
hospital with several bruises and a cut lip.
``The course was dangerous and risky. Let's hope the next stages
are scheduled on safer roads,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Balducci</ENAMEX> said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Balducci</ENAMEX>, who completed the stage in three hours, 27.55 minutes,
edged <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Denmark</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lars Michaelsen</ENAMEX> at the finish line. Another Dane,
veteran <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rolf Sorensen</ENAMEX>, placed fourth, behind <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italy</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roberto
Petito</ENAMEX>.
Thursday's second stage of 164 kilometers (103 miles) will take
cyclists from <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Sorrento</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Baia Domizia</ENAMEX>.
The Tirreno-Adriatico, the opening event of the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Italian</ENAMEX> cycling
season which is considered a warmup for the Milan-to-San Remo,
crosses central <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Italy</ENAMEX> from the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tyrrhenian</ENAMEX> to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Adriatic sea</ENAMEX>.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Sports-Cycling-Tirreno-Adriatico, 1st Ld-Writethru; CT:s;
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-11-98 1502EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

