<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980213.1320 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/13/1998 14:35:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2122 &Cx1f; wstm-
r f &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Australia-India-Qanta     02-13 0223
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Australia-India-Qantas,0225 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Qantas to run daily flights between Australia and India
</HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">CANBERRA</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Australia</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qantas</ENAMEX> will almost double its flights
between <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Australia</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">India</ENAMEX> by August in the search for new markets
untouched by the crippling <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Asian</ENAMEX> financial crisis.
This move comes barely a month after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qantas</ENAMEX> suspended a number
of services between <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Australia</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Indonesia</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Thailand</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Malaysia</ENAMEX> in
the wake of the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Asian</ENAMEX> economic crisis.
The airline has also cut all flights to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">South Korea</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qantas</ENAMEX> plans daily flights between <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Sydney</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bombay</ENAMEX>, up from
the current four flights a week, to boost business and tourism ties
with <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">India</ENAMEX>, the airline announced Friday.
In a joint statement with Tourism Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Andrew Thomson</ENAMEX>, it
said two new flights would leave <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bombay</ENAMEX> on Monday and Tuesday
nights from March 30, with the third departing each Thursday from
August 6.
This will add nearly 700 seats a week on the route.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thomson</ENAMEX>, in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">India</ENAMEX> to talk to tourism leaders, said the flights
would provide extra support to the growing tourism market.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qantas</ENAMEX>' <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">India</ENAMEX> manager <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Khursheed Lam</ENAMEX> said the airline was working
closely with the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Australian</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tourist Commission</ENAMEX> to develop greater
awareness of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Australia</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Indian</ENAMEX> market.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qantas</ENAMEX> will also appoint a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bombay</ENAMEX>-based public relations
consultant.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Australia-India-Qantas; CT:f;
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-13-98 1435EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

