<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980213.1363 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/13/1998 15:03:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2167 &Cx1f; wstm-
u i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Iraq-Deputyminister 1stLd-Writethru   02-13 0565
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Iraq-Deputy minister, 1st Ld-Writethru </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
With BC-Iraq
</HEADLINE>
&UR; Iraqi minister rebutts Sandy Berger's allegations &QL;
&UR; Eds: COMBINES lede and add &QL;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">United Kingdom</ENAMEX>, are trying to achieve.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Al-Qaysi</ENAMEX> took issue with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Berger</ENAMEX>'s saying that any <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> strike
would be aimed at eliminating ``the threat of the use of weapons of
mass destruction by <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Berger</ENAMEX> ``considers <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UNSCOM</ENAMEX> to be the body responsible for making
such a determination,'' he said, referring to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N. Special
Commission</ENAMEX> whose inspectors are charged with searching for <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX>'s
mass destruction weapons.
``To my mind, and to that of my government, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UNSCOM</ENAMEX> has not made
any reference to an existing threat, as of now, by <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> against its
neighbors on account of the existence of weapons of mass
destruction. Its reports indicate the contrary.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Al-Qaysi</ENAMEX> also criticized <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">British</ENAMEX> Foreign Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robin Cook</ENAMEX>
for saying earlier this week that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> posed a threat because it
still possessed weapons of mass destruction.
``Nothing can be further from the truth. He should check
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UNSCOM</ENAMEX>'s report.''
Referring to the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">British</ENAMEX> threat to attack <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> if it
does not give unfettered access to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> inspectors, whom <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Baghdad</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>
has barred from a number of suspected weapons sites on grounds of
national sovereignty, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">al-Qaysi</ENAMEX> said the two powers were not seeking
to reinforce the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Special Commission</ENAMEX>.
``The objective is not <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UNSCOM</ENAMEX>. The objective is to use military
force per se.''
The deputy foreign minister spelled out the location of the
eight presidential sites that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraq</ENAMEX> has offered to open up to
inspectors appointed by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> Secretary-General Kofi Annan.
He said three of the sites were in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Baghdad</ENAMEX>, three were
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Salah-Eddine</ENAMEX> (an area near <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraqi</ENAMEX> leader <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saddam Hussein</ENAMEX>'s home town
of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tikrit</ENAMEX>, north of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Baghdad</ENAMEX>), one was in the northern region of
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ninawa</ENAMEX> (also known as <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Mosul</ENAMEX>), and one was in the southern city of
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Basra</ENAMEX>.
It was first time that a senior <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Iraqi</ENAMEX> official had identified
the eight sites.
</TEXT>
&UR; bm-jbm
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Iraq-Deputy minister, 1st Ld-Writethru; CT:i;
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-13-98 1503EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

