<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980311.1361 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/11/1998 15:06:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2108 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-France-Papon     03-11 0330
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-France-Papon </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Civil parties continue final arguments in Papon case
</HEADLINE>
&UR; By NICOLAS MARMIE &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">BORDEAUX</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">France</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Lawyers charged ahead Wednesday with
final arguments in their attempts to prove former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cabinet</ENAMEX> Minister
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Maurice Papon</ENAMEX> ordered the arrests that led to deportation of 1,690
Jews during World War II.
It was the third day of the marathon final arguments of some two
dozen lawyers representing of alleged victims and their families of
the roundups that occurred while <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Papon</ENAMEX> was the head of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jewish
Affairs Services</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bordeaux</ENAMEX> prefecture.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Papon</ENAMEX>, who along with his lawyers will have the chance to speak
later this month in the war crimes trial, remained silent as the
civil party lawyers made their case.
``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Maurice Papon</ENAMEX> is afflicted with the syndrome of the German
shepherd: always faithful whoever is the master,'' said lawyer
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jean-Serge Lorach</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Papon</ENAMEX> maintains that he had no major power was just following
orders he received from his boss, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Maurice Sabatier</ENAMEX>, who was the
prefect of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bordeaux</ENAMEX> during the war.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Raymond Blet</ENAMEX>, another civil party lawyer who spoke Wednesday,
cast in doubt <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Papon</ENAMEX>'s claim that he actually helped the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">French</ENAMEX>
resistance during the war.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Papon</ENAMEX>, who was chief police inspector for the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bordeaux</ENAMEX> region
during World War II and later budget minister, is the
highest-ranking official of the pro-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nazi</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Vichy</ENAMEX> regime to stand
trial for complicity in crimes against humanity.
He is accused of signing the arrest orders that led to the
deportation of 1,690 Jews from <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bordeaux</ENAMEX> during World War II. They
later died at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nazi</ENAMEX> death camp at <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Auschwitz</ENAMEX>.
Civil party lawyers are to continue making their arguments all
this week. A verdict is expected by the end of March.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Papon</ENAMEX>'s trial is now in its sixth month.
On Wednesday, seven more civil party lawyers were to address the
three judges and nine jurors with their final arguments.
(parf-dgs)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-France-Papon; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-11-98 1506EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

