<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980227.0474 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 08:01:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2379 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Croatia-Bosnia-Oil     02-27 0408
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Croatia-Bosnia-Oil </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Croatia's oil company confiscates oil from Bosnian firm
</HEADLINE>
&UR; By SNJEZANA VUKIC &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">ZAGREB</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Croatia</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Amid efforts to crack down on its
longtime debtors, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Croatia</ENAMEX>'s state-run oil company Friday
confiscated 30,000 tons of oil products it had provided to a
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bosnian</ENAMEX> company, the state-run news agency <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">HINA</ENAMEX> reported.
Officials with the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Croatian</ENAMEX> oil company <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">INA</ENAMEX> said the move was
done for economic reasons, but it is likely to erode already-tense
relations between the two neighbors.
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bosnia</ENAMEX>'s state-owned oil company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Energopetrol</ENAMEX>, owes <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">INA</ENAMEX> dlrs
3.8 million. Friday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">INA</ENAMEX> confiscated 30,000 tons of oil and oil
products it had provided to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Energopetrol</ENAMEX>. The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bosnian</ENAMEX> company had
not paid for the products stored in the southern <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Croatian</ENAMEX> port of
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ploce</ENAMEX>.
``This was done suddenly, without any negotiations, discussions
or warning,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Aziz Tukulj</ENAMEX>, director of domestic sales for
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Energopetrol</ENAMEX>. ``My personal feeling is that this is pure
bullying.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Energopetrol</ENAMEX> owes money to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">INA</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tukulj</ENAMEX> said, but wasn't sure how
much. He added that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">INA</ENAMEX> owes money to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Energopetrol</ENAMEX> and its parent
company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Energoinvest</ENAMEX>.
He said contracts between the two companies require negotiations
be undertaken to resolve disputes.
A spokesman from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">INA</ENAMEX> could not be reached to confirm <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tukulj</ENAMEX>'s
comments.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">INA</ENAMEX> recently announced that it would start punishing debtors
because unpaid bills totaling dlrs 141 million threaten its
business.
Some debtors, like <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Croatia</ENAMEX>'s electric-power industry, airline
and railway, promised to pay up immediately.
It is doubtful whether <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bosnia</ENAMEX>, whose economy is in ruins after a
devastating war, can pay its debts.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tukulj</ENAMEX> said the confiscation will not create shortages in
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bosnia</ENAMEX>.
But the move is likely to have political consequences.
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bosnia</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Muslim</ENAMEX>-led leadership was outraged by a recent speech
by <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Croatian</ENAMEX> President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Franjo Tudjman</ENAMEX>, in which he justified his
support for the wartime <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bosnian</ENAMEX> Croat substate.
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bosnian</ENAMEX> leaders, as well as international officials, are leery
of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tudjman</ENAMEX>'s intentions towards <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bosnia</ENAMEX>. They interpreted his
remarks as an indication of his continued desire to annex a part of
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bosnia</ENAMEX>.
In addition, the two countries have failed to agree on terms for
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bosnia</ENAMEX> to lease part of the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ploce</ENAMEX> port.
The confiscation by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">INA</ENAMEX> ``looks like some kind of (political)
pressure,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tukulj</ENAMEX> said.
(sv/scl/sl)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Croatia-Bosnia-Oil; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0801EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

