<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980227.0494 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 08:17:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2399 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Russia-Ukraine 1stLd-Writethru   02-27 0647
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Russia-Ukraine, 1st Ld-Writethru </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Russia, Ukraine sign plan, Yeltsin claims progress in major
</HEADLINE>
disputes &QL;
&UR; Eds: UPDATES throughout with joint statement of two presidents,
UPGRADES attribution, CORRECTS in graf 14 that An-70 is cargo
plane. &QL;
&UR; By ANNA DOLGOV &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">MOSCOW</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Presidents <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Leonid Kuchma</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ukraine</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Boris
Yeltsin</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russia</ENAMEX> signed an economic cooperation plan Friday, and
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yeltsin</ENAMEX> claimed they resolved even more nagging problems.
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russia</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ukraine</ENAMEX> share similar cultures and languages, and
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ukraine</ENAMEX> was ruled from <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Moscow</ENAMEX> for centuries. But while the two
Slavic neighbors see themselves as natural partners, their
relations since the breakup of the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Soviet Union</ENAMEX> have been bedeviled
by a number of disputes _ <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Black Sea</ENAMEX> naval bases, border problems
and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ukraine</ENAMEX>'s natural gas debts.
``We have covered the entire list of questions and discussed how
we will be tackling them,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yeltsin</ENAMEX> was quoted as saying by the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ITAR-Tass news agency</ENAMEX>. ``I must say there are no unsettled problems
any more. We have solved them all.''
But his sweeping statement contained no details, and gave no
indication of how the disputes could be resolved. Their solution
would require a compromise between the two nations' parliaments.
A major dispute concerns a broad political treaty calling for
border demarcation, which the two presidents signed last May.
In effect, the treaty amounts to <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> recognition of
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ukraine</ENAMEX>'s sovereignty and borders, and the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ukrainian</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">parliament</ENAMEX> has
already ratified it. However, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russia</ENAMEX> has stalled ratification,
trying to tie it to an agreement that would permit the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> navy
to use a naval base on <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ukraine</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Crimean peninsula</ENAMEX> for at least 20
more years.
In their joint statement issued after the talks, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yeltsin</ENAMEX> and
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kuchma</ENAMEX> called for the fastest possible ratification of the treaty,
saying it would create a ``strong legal foundation'' for bilateral
ties and help stability in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Europe</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kuchma</ENAMEX> assured <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yeltsin</ENAMEX> that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ukraine</ENAMEX> would not join <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NATO</ENAMEX>,
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yeltsin</ENAMEX>'s spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sergei Yastrzhembsky</ENAMEX> said, according to the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Interfax news agency</ENAMEX>. The <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> leadership has staunchly opposed
the western alliance's expansion into Eastern <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Europe</ENAMEX>.
In their joint statement, released by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="FACILITY">Kremlin</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, the two
leaders also pledged to consult each other regularly on their
approaches to relations with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NATO</ENAMEX> and, in particular, their action
within the framework of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NATO</ENAMEX>'s Partnership for Peace program.
Last year, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> officials assailed <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ukraine</ENAMEX> for holding joint
naval exercises with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NATO</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Black Sea</ENAMEX> _ an area <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Moscow</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>
considers its own turf.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kuchma</ENAMEX> has said repeatedly that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ukraine</ENAMEX> would remain neutral for
the foreseeable future.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yeltsin</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kuchma</ENAMEX> also called for developing the stagnant
relations between the members of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Commonwealth of Independent
States</ENAMEX>, a loose coalition of former <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Soviet</ENAMEX> republics. In the past,
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russia</ENAMEX> has often claimed that <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ukraine</ENAMEX> was undermining efforts at
closer cooperation within the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CIS</ENAMEX>.
A major goal of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kuchma</ENAMEX>'s four-day state visit was the signing of
a 10-year economic program aimed at doubling the two nations' trade
turnover, which fell to dlrs 14 billion last year, down dlrs 2.5
billion from 1996.
The two presidents on Friday signed the plan, which calls for
cooperation in the metallurgy, fuel, energy, aircraft building,
missile, space and chemical industries. A major project is joint
manufacturing of An-70 cargo planes, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION"><ENAMEX TYPE="FACILITY">Kremlin</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> statement said.
The program also calls for coordination of economic reforms and
joint improvement of social programs in the two countries, where
many people have become impoverished during the chaotic post-<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Soviet</ENAMEX>
transition to capitalism.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kuchma</ENAMEX> also planned to visit <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Russian</ENAMEX> gas giant <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gazprom</ENAMEX>, most
likely to discuss <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ukraine</ENAMEX>'s dlrs 1.2 billion debt to the company.
(pvs/vi/ji)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Russia-Ukraine, 1st Ld-Writethru; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0817EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

