<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980227.0501 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 08:23:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2406 &Cx1f; wstm-
r I &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Turkey-Attack 3rdLd-Writethru   02-27 0186
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Turkey-Attack, 3rd Ld-Writethru </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Gunmen wound 16 Turkish soldiers in raid
</HEADLINE>
&UR; Eds: UPDATES with claim of responsibility &QL;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">ISTANBUL</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Turkey</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Three gunmen tossed two hand grenades
into the garden of a military outpost during a roll-call in
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Istanbul</ENAMEX> on Friday after opening fire on a sentry, wounding 16
soldiers, reports said.
Leftist and Kurdish guerrilla groups phoning several media
organizations in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Istanbul</ENAMEX> claimed responsibility for the assault.
The attack appeared to be the latest example of the
collaboration between the leftist <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Revolutionary People's Salvation
Party-Front</ENAMEX> and Kurdish guerrillas, who are fighting for autonomy
in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Turkey</ENAMEX>'s southeast.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anatolia news agency</ENAMEX> said the attackers fled the scene by a
car immediately after the attack at around 8 a.m. (0600 GMT) in
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Gaziosmanpasa district</ENAMEX>, on the outskirts of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Istanbul</ENAMEX>.
The injured, including an officer, were in stable condition,
private <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTV</ENAMEX> television said.
The war between Kurdish guerrillas and government forces in
southeastern <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Turkey</ENAMEX> has killed 37,000 people since 1984.
(sh/vls)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Turkey-Attack, 3rd Ld-Writethru; CT:I;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0823EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

