<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980213.1380 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/13/1998 15:44:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2227 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-PuertoRico-HostageKil     02-13 0243
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Puerto Rico-Hostage Killed,0246 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Police discover dismembered body of man kidnapped Wednesday
</HEADLINE>
&UR; By HILARIO DE LEON &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">CAGUAS</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Puerto Rico</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Kidnappers kept their promise to kill
a store owner they took hostage and police found the man's
dismembered and decapitated body Friday wrapped in plastic garbage
bags.
Police confirmed Friday that the body found along a highway in
this municipality 15 miles south of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">San Juan</ENAMEX> belonged to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jorge
Hernandez</ENAMEX>, 49.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hernandez</ENAMEX> was kidnapped from his small, neighborhood store in
the town of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Trujillo Alto</ENAMEX> at 10 p.m. Wednesday, police said. His
kidnappers demanded a ransom of dlrs 1 million, but negotiations
broke off at noon Thursday.
Police gave no details about the negotiations with the
kidnappers for the return of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hernandez</ENAMEX>.
The store owner's body was found with the arms and head cut off
and the parts stuffed in separate garbage bags. A passerby called
police to report the body alongside the road.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Puerto Rico Police</ENAMEX> Superintendent <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pedro Toledo</ENAMEX> urged people who
might be targeted by kidnappers to be alert.
``There has been an increase in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Puerto Rico</ENAMEX> in this kind of
thing and some of these bands of kidnappers are made up of
foreigners,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Toledo</ENAMEX> said.
While some <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Latin American</ENAMEX> countries such as <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Mexico</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Colombia</ENAMEX>
have suffered from a rash of kidnappings in recent years, the crime
has not been common in this <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">U.S.</ENAMEX> commonwealth.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Puerto Rico-Hostage Killed; CT:i;
(REG:CRB;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-13-98 1544EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

