<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980227.0487 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 08:09:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2392 &Cx1f; wstm-
u i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Israel-Rabin     02-27 0300
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Israel-Rabin,0300 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Friend of Rabin's assassin regretted praying for Rabin's death
</HEADLINE>
&UR; By DANNA HARMAN &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">JERUSALEM</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Taking the stand in her own defense, a friend
of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yitzhak Rabin</ENAMEX>'s assassin said Friday that she regretted calling
the prime minister a traitor and praying for his death.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Margalit Har-Shefi</ENAMEX>, 22, has pleaded innocent to charges that she
failed to report <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yigal Amir</ENAMEX>'s plan to kill <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rabin</ENAMEX>. She took the
stand for more than four hours Friday in a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tel Aviv</ENAMEX> magistrate's
court.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Amir</ENAMEX>, 27, is serving a life sentence for the November 1995
assassination of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rabin</ENAMEX> at a <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Tel Aviv</ENAMEX> peace rally. Newspaper reports
have said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Amir</ENAMEX> was infatuated with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Har-Shefi</ENAMEX> and may have been
trying to impress her by killing the prime minister.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Har-Shefi</ENAMEX> acknowledged she told police interrogators that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rabin</ENAMEX>
was a traitor and that she prayed for him to have a heart attack
and die. She said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rabin</ENAMEX>'s murder was ``a black stain on <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Israel</ENAMEX>,''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Israel radio</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Israel army radio</ENAMEX> reported.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Har-Shefi</ENAMEX> said she heard <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Amir</ENAMEX> talk about killing <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rabin</ENAMEX> but did
not tell the police because she did not believe he was serious.
Instead, she turned to her community rabbi in the Jewish <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Bank</ENAMEX>
settlement of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Beit El</ENAMEX> and told him about <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Amir</ENAMEX>'s statements. The
rabbi said called the talk about killing <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rabin</ENAMEX> ``nonsense,'' and
said Jews are prohibited from killing one another, the radio
reports said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Har-Shefi</ENAMEX> described <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Amir</ENAMEX> as an ``original thinker,'' as well as
delusional and a liar.
She also denied accusations made by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Amir</ENAMEX>'s brother, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hagai</ENAMEX>, that
she joined an anti-<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Arab</ENAMEX> underground movement. She said she gave the
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Amir</ENAMEX> brothers false information regarding the location of a weapons
and ammunition cache when they asked her to help organize such a
movement.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Israel-Rabin; CT:i;
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0809EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
