<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980308.0201 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/08/1998 06:26:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2106 &Cx1f; wstm-
r i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-Turkey-Yugoslavia-Kos     03-08 0243
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-Turkey-Yugoslavia-Kosovo,0242 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Ethnic Albanians in Turkey protest Serb attacks in Kosovo
</HEADLINE>
&UR; AP Photos IST101-102 &QL;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">ISTANBUL</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Turkey</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Some 1,500 ethnic Albanians marched
Sunday in downtown <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Istanbul</ENAMEX>, burning <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Serbian</ENAMEX> flags to protest the
killings of ethnic Albanians by <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Serb</ENAMEX> police in southern <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Serb</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Kosovo</ENAMEX>
province.
The police barred the crowd from reaching the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Yugoslavian</ENAMEX>
consulate in downtown <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE"><ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Istanbul</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, but allowed them to demonstrate on
nearby streets.
``Stop the bloodshed in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Kosovo</ENAMEX>,'' the protesters chanted.
Meanwhile in the capital, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Ankara</ENAMEX>, a few hundred ethnic Albanians
laid a black wreath at the gate of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Yugoslavian</ENAMEX> embassy.
Ethnic Albanians comprise 90 percent of the population in
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Kosovo</ENAMEX>, but Serbs maintain control through a large military and
police presence. <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Serbian</ENAMEX> police say they are trying to eliminate
the pro-independence <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kosovo Liberation Army</ENAMEX> and restore order.
At least 51 people were reported killed in clashes between <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Serb</ENAMEX>
police and ethnic Albanians in the troubled region in recent days.
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Turkey</ENAMEX>, worried about civil war in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Kosovo</ENAMEX> spilling to the whole
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Balkans</ENAMEX>, urged all <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Balkan</ENAMEX> states to sign a joint declaration that
the <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Kosovo</ENAMEX> crisis be solved peacefully and without any change of
borders.
Turks feel they have special ties to the whole region, which
they ruled for hundreds of years during the Ottoman Empire. They
also share <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Islam</ENAMEX> with the ethnic Albanians.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Turkey-Yugoslavia-Kosovo; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:MEST;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-08-98 0626EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

