<DOC>
<DOCNO> APW19980227.0465 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 07:55:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2370 &Cx1f; wstm-
u i &Cx13;  &Cx11;  BC-India-Politics 3rdLd-Writethru   02-27 0495
</HEADER>
<BODY>
<SLUG> BC-India-Politics, 3rd Ld-Writethru,0495 </SLUG>
<HEADLINE>
Anti-election strike, protest shut down Kashmiri capital
</HEADLINE>
&UR; Eds: ADDS six separatist leaders arrested for asking people to
boycott the voting, details. ADDS byline. No pickup. &QL;
&UR; AP Photos planned &QL;
&UR; By KRISHNAN GURUSWAMY &QC;
&UR; Associated Press Writer &QC;

<TEXT>
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">SRINAGAR</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">India</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AP</ENAMEX>) _ Police fired tear gas to disperse
stone-throwing protesters during an anti-election strike in the
capital of volatile <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Kashmir</ENAMEX> state Friday, a day ahead of
parliamentary elections.
Local news agencies reported no injuries in the clashes.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Muslim</ENAMEX> groups who want <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Kashmir</ENAMEX> to be independent of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">India</ENAMEX> have
called another strike in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Srinagar</ENAMEX> on Saturday, as well as an
election boycott. Their opposition and cold weather in the
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Himalayan</ENAMEX> state are likely to keep turnout low.
Shops were closed and government offices deserted Friday. Small
groups of protesters gathered at several spots in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Srinagar</ENAMEX>.
Eight leaders of the separatist <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">All Party Hurriyat Conference</ENAMEX>
have been arrested since Wednesday for asking people to boycott the
voting, said state Chief Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ashok Jaitly</ENAMEX>.
On Friday, angry <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hurriyat</ENAMEX> activists hurled stones at
paramilitary forces protesting the arrest of their leaders. Police
fired 150 tear gas shells to disperse the protesters who fought
hit-and-run battles throughout Friday.
Temperatures were just above freezing in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Srinagar</ENAMEX>, with a foot
(30 centimeters) of snow on the ground following storms that shut
down air and road traffic earlier in the week.
Voting scheduled in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Srinagar</ENAMEX> and elsewhere in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">India</ENAMEX> on Saturday,
the fourth of six days of balloting, will wrap up all but a few
parliamentary races. Counting begins the following Monday, and a
new parliament and prime minister are expected to be seated by
mid-March.
Paramilitary troops took up positions Thursday at schools and
government offices, where the voting will be held in <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Srinagar</ENAMEX>, 600
kilometers (375 miles) north of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">New Delhi</ENAMEX>. Suspected militants
lobbed a grenade into a school as troops took up position, but no
one was injured.
Paramilitary forces guarded 1,000 polling stations set up in
<ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Srinagar</ENAMEX> district, where 850,000 voters are registered. The state
capital has been the center of a nine-year insurgency by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Muslims</ENAMEX>
militants fighting for independence from <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">India</ENAMEX> or for merger with
neighboring <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Pakistan</ENAMEX>, which is officially <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Islamic</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Kashmir</ENAMEX> is the
only <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Muslim</ENAMEX> majority state in overwhelmingly <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hindu</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">India</ENAMEX>.
The main parliamentary contenders _ the centrist <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress party</ENAMEX>
stability a central issue in the campaign.
More than 70 people died in election-related violence during the
first three voting days and during campaigning, mostly in the
eastern state of <ENAMEX TYPE="GPE">Bihar</ENAMEX>, where unrest is blamed on caste tensions
and criminals. Another 58 people died in a series of bombings in
southern <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">India</ENAMEX> linked to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hindu</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Muslim</ENAMEX> tensions exacerbated by
campaign rhetoric.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-India-Politics, 3rd Ld-Writethru; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0755EST
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

